<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A commentarie of M. Iohn Caluine, vpon the Epistle to the Colossians. And translated into English by R.V.</title>
            <title>Commentarii in quatuor Pauli epistolas. English. Selections</title>
            <author>Calvin, Jean, 1509-1564.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1581</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 215 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 51 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A17648</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4403</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S107211</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99842913</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99842913</idno>
            <idno type="VID">7610</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A17648)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 7610)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 877:01)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A commentarie of M. Iohn Caluine, vpon the Epistle to the Colossians. And translated into English by R.V.</title>
                  <title>Commentarii in quatuor Pauli epistolas. English. Selections</title>
                  <author>Calvin, Jean, 1509-1564.</author>
                  <author>Vaux, Robert.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 86 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Thomas Purfoote, and are to be sold at his shop ouer against S. Sepulchers Church,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1581]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>R.V. = Robert Vaux.</note>
                  <note>A translation of part of: Commentarii in quatuor Pauli epistolas.</note>
                  <note>Publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>Usually found bound with STC 4401.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Colossians --  Commentaries.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Corinne Vieracker</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Corinne Vieracker</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:7610:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7610:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi> Commentarie of <hi>M. Iohn Caluine,</hi> vpon the Epiſtle to the Coloſsians.</p>
            <p>And tranſlated into Engliſh by R. V.</p>
            <q>Pray for the peace of Hieruſalem, they shall proſper that loue thee. <bibl>Pſal. 122.6.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>AT LONDON, <hi>Printed by Thomas</hi> Purfoote, and are to be ſold <hi>at his ſhop ouer againſt S. Sepulchers Church.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:7610:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7610:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO THE VVORSHIPFVL and reuerende fathers maiſter Noel,</hi> Deane of Poules, M. Mullins Archdeacon of London, <hi>maiſter D. Walker, Archdeacon of Eſſex, &amp; maiſter</hi> Towers profeſſor of diuinity, his ſinguler good <hi>friendes and Patrons,</hi> R. V. <hi>wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth all health.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>MAny in the dedicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of their trauails are accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stomed to ſet forth the praiſes of ſuch parſons as they do dedicate the ſame vnto. And ſurely J thinke it not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe if flattery be abſent. For who is ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that <hi>virtus laudata creſcit,</hi> praiſe vertue, and it ſhall encreaſe. I ſpeake not this right worſhipful and reuerende fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, to the ende that J meane to do the like to you, although no man that knoweth you but he will ſay you worthelye deſerue the ſame: for if J ſhoulde either praiſe your learning or diligence in your vocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb facs="tcp:7610:3"/> which euery where is knowen, or your, godly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſation which vnto your nigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt frendes is well tried, or your libera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity which all thoſe that haue neede, but ſpetially the Godly poore haue found and daily do fynde, who might iuſtly reprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d me: but letting paſſe theſe thinges to the conſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of vpright iudges, I purpoſe to ſhew and that very brieflye what hath moued me to dedicate this preſent booke vnto your worſhippes. you knowe that I receaued at your handes (that worthye man maiſter D. Watts beynge then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liue, whom with reuerence I remember) that liuinge which J haue: and althoughe you ſell not your benefices (as manye in theſe dayes do) yet reaſon woulde that J ſhould not remaine vnthankefull for the ſame, though it were a greate deale leſſe then it is. And wheras want of abilitye
<pb facs="tcp:7610:3"/> vvould not ſuffer me to reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pence other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvyſe your good will, yet rather then ſtill <hi>I</hi> ſhould continue vnthankeful, I choſe this litle commentary of that worthye fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther M. <hi>Caluine</hi> to ſupply that which els might be left vndon: vvherin J vviſh that my hart lay open to be vievved: then vvould you not more regard the thinge it ſelfe, vvhich no doubt is vvorthy the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the good vvil of him that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenteth the ſame vnto you. Fare you vvel. At high Easter the firſt of Nouember.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours to commaund <hi>R. V.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="argument">
            <pb facs="tcp:7610:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7610:4"/>
            <head>¶ <hi>The Argument vpon the epiſtle of. S.</hi> Paule to the Coloſsians by maiſter Caluin.</head>
            <p>THere were three Cities one neare to another in <hi>Phrygia,</hi> of which <hi>Paul</hi> maketh menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in this Epiſtle: <hi>Laodicea, Hierapolis,</hi> and <hi>Coloſſae,</hi> which <hi>Oroſius</hi> teſtifyeth to haue falle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> downe while <hi>Nero</hi> raigned, with an Earthquake. And ſo not long after this Epiſtle was written: three fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous churches were deſtroyed with a lamentable and fearful chaunce. A notable ſpectacle forſooth of God his iudgement: if wee lacked not eyes. The <hi>Coloſſians</hi> indeede were firſt enſtructed in the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, not by <hi>Paul,</hi> but faithfully and purely by <hi>Epa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaus</hi> and other miniſters. But by and by Satan according to his ſolemne and perpetuall cuſtome, crept in with his darnell and tares, that he mighte ouerthrow the right faith there. Some thinke that there were two kind of men which aſſaied to lead away the <hi>Coloſſians</hi> from the purity of the Goſpel. For on the one ſyde the Philoſophers by diſputinge of the ſtarres of deſtenye and ſuch like tryfles, on on the other ſyde the Iewes by vrging and enfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing their ceremonies, caſt abroad many miſtes to ouerthrow Chriſt, but they which thinke ſo are mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued therunto by an ouerlight coniecture orgeſſe. be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cauſe forſoth <hi>Paule</hi> maketh mention of thrones and
<pb facs="tcp:7610:5"/> powers and heauenly creatures. And whereas they adde alſo the name of <hi>Elements,</hi> it is more then ridiculous. But becauſe I am not purpoſed to confute the opinions of other, I will onely ſpeake mine owne minde, and that which by ſounde rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons I may gather.</p>
            <p>Firſt of all, it appeareth ſufficiently by the words of Paule, that the vaclets practiſed this, (namely) to mingle Chriſt with Moſes, and together with the Goſpell to retayne the ſhadowes of the Law: whervpon it is very likely that they were Iewes. And for that they paynted out their crafty dealing with beautifull colours: therefore Paule calleth it vayne Philoſophie. Although withal (in my iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) he reſpected in this worde the ſlye reaſons wherewith they dalyed, which in dede were ſharp or ſubtile, but yet vayne and prophane. For they imagined an entraunce or acceſſe to God by the Angels, and many ſuche like reuelations brought they in, as are conteyned in the bookes of Diony<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuis of the heauenly Hiera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>chie, drawne out of the ſchole of the Platonicall Philoſophers. This is the principall marke wherevnto he leueleth, that he may teache all things to haue their being in Chriſt: and that therefore he alone is enough and enough to the Coloſſians. But he keepeth this or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. After his accuſtomed ſuperſcription, by pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing them, he maketh them the more attentiue to heare him. After that, to thende he may ſhutte vp the waye agaynſt all newe and ſtraunge inuenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<pb facs="tcp:7610:5"/> he geueth a teſtimoniall to the doctrine which afore they had receiued by <hi>Epaphras.</hi> after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward whilſt he wiſheth them encreaſe of faith from the Lord, he meaneth that as yet ſomewhat is wanting: that he may make a waye for him ſelfe more firmly to inſtruct them. On the contrary part he ſetteth forth the grace of god to themward with the titles to the ſame belonginge, leſt they ſhoulde make ſmall account thereof. Then foloweth an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, in which he teacheth that all the parts of our ſaluation are planted in Chriſt only, that they ſhould ſeeke nothing elſewhere, and he mentioneth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they haue obtayned in Chriſte, whatſoeuer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ood things there are, to the end they may the more dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently haue regarde to kepe him to the ende. And truly euen this one Chapter is vtterly enoughe, to make vs account of this Epiſtle, although it be but ſhort, as of an in comperable treaſure. For what is greater in all the heauenlye doctrine, than to haue Chriſte ſkilfully paynted out: that we praye ſee his vertue and power, his office, and all the fruites and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modities which come from him to vs? For euen in this one thing ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>fely doe we differ from the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, that whereas we be both called Chriſtians, and profeſſe our ſelues to beleeue in Chriſt, they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe to themſelues a Chriſt that is torne, deformed, made voide of his ſtrength and power, ſpoyled of his office: to be ſhort, ſuche a Chriſte as is rather a ghoſte or ſhadowe then a Chriſte in deede: but we embrace him as here he is deſcribed and ſet out by
<pb facs="tcp:7610:6"/> 
               <hi>Paule,</hi> namely a liuely &amp; effectuous Chriſt. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, to ſpeake it at a word, this Epiſtle ſheweth the difference betwene the true Chriſt and the fained. than which nothing can be wiſhed ether better or more excellent. About the ende of the firſt chapiter, he ſeeketh to winne authoritie vnto him agayne by meanes of his calling &amp; perſon: and he doth hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably ſet out the worthines of the Goſpel. In the ſeconde Chapiter he openeth more playnely the cauſe wherfore he did write: namely that he might preuent the daunger which he ſawe to hang ouer theire heades, where by the waye he treateth of his loue toward them to the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>de they might acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege he had a care for their ſauegarde. From that he paſſeth ouer to exhorting, wherewith he appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his doctrine afore going as it were to a preſent vſe: For hee alſo biddeth them ſettle them ſelues in Chriſte alone, and condemneth it of vanitie, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer it is, that is without Chriſt. He ſpeaketh by name of Circumciſion, abſtinence of meates, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther outward exerciſes: vnto which they doe ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thwartly and amiſſe binde the ſeruice of God. He ſpeak'th alſo of the prepoſterous ſeruice of Angels whom they dep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ed in Chriſtes roome. And being moued by occaſion of circumciſion he doth alſo by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> waye touch what office and nature of ceremonies was. Wherevpon he determineth that they were abrogated by Chriſt. And theſe things doth he fill y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> end of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſecond chapiter. In y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> third chapiter, he ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true dueties of godlines, wherwith y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lorde
<pb facs="tcp:7610:6"/> wil haue vs b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fied, againſt thoſe vaine precepts to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> obſeruing wherof y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> falſe apoſtle wold conſtrayn the faithfull. And he beginneth at the ſpring head it ſelfe, that is to ſaye, at mortification of the fleſhe &amp; newnes of life: from whence he draweth brooke, that is to ſay, particular exhortations: ſome, which belong to all Chriſtians alyke: and ſome, which priuatly partayne to certayne perſons, according to the reaſon and manner of their calling. In the beginning of the fourth Chapiter hee goeth on ſtill with the ſame argument: after that when he hath commended himſelfe to their prayers, he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clareth by many tokens howe greatly hee loueth them, and is deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to poruide and care for their ſaluation.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:7610:7"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:7610:7"/>
            <head>¶ A Commentarie of M. <hi>John Caluine</hi> vpon the Epiſtle of Paule to the Coloſſians, <hi>done into Engliſhe by</hi> R. V.</head>
            <q>
               <p n="1">1 Paule an Apoſtle of Ieſus Chriſt by the will of God, and Timothie a brother.</p>
               <p n="2">2 To the Saintes which are at Coloſſa, and to the faithfull bretheren in Chriſt: grace vnto you, and peace from God our Father, and the Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="3">3 We giue thankes to God and the Father of our Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, alwayes praying for you.</p>
               <p n="4">4 Hauing heard of your faith which is in Chriſt Ieſus, and loue toward all Saintes.</p>
               <p n="5">5 For the hope layde vp for you in heauen, whereof you haue heard before by the worde of truth, that is to ſay, of the Goſpell.</p>
               <p n="6">6 Which is come vnto you as alſo in the vniuerſall Worlde it doth bring forth fruite and is encreaſed, as in you alſo, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the day which you heard, &amp; knew the grace of God in truth.</p>
               <p n="7">7 As alſo you haue learned of Epaphras our beloued fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low ſeruaunt, who is towardes you a faithfull Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="8">8 Who alſo hath made knowne vnto vs your loue in the ſpirite.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>PAule an Apoſtle.) <hi>It</hi>
               </hi> hath bene alreadye often declared to what purpoſe theſe ſuperſcriptions doe belong. Becauſe the Coloſſians had neuer ſeene him: and that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his authoritie was not as yet ſo firme amonges them that his owne name alone was ſufficient: he doth at the beginning tell them that hee was ordayned the Apoſtle of Chriſt by the will of God. Whereof it followed that he did not raſhly in that he wrote to them he know not: becauſe hee did the Embaſſade, committed to him of God.
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:7610:8"/> For he was not appoynted to one Church, but his Apoſtleſhip had way to all. The name of, Saints, which he attributeth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, is more honourable: but in that he calleth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>faithfull bretheren,</hi> he doth more gently allure the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to hearken vnto him. The reſt you may ſeeke out of the former Epiſtles.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3 We giue thankes.)</hi> He commendeth the faith and loue of the Coloſſians, wherby he may y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> better confirme the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cheerefully to go forward and to be conſtant. Beſide that wheras he ſheweth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he hath ſuch a perſwaſion of them, hee winneth vnto him their harts, whereby they may be the more ready &amp; apt to receiue his doctrine. Alwayes muſt you marke, that in ſteede of gratulation or reioicing, he vſeth giuing thankes. whereby he teacheth, that in all reioicing ſtrayight way the remembrance of Gods good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ought to come in mind: becauſe it is his good gift whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer it is, that happeneth vnto vs ioyfull and happy. Moreouer by his example hee doth admoniſhe vs, that wee not onelye bee thankefull for thoſe thinges which the Lorde doth beſtowe vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ourſelues, but for that alſo which he beſtoweth vpon others. But for what thinges doeth hee giue thankes to the Lorde? for the fayth and loue of the Coloſſians. Therefore he confeſſeth that both of them are giuen of God: or elſe his thankesgiuing were [but] fayned. And what haue we but of his liberali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie? If ſo be that the very ſmalleſt thinges that we haue, come from him, how muche rather muſt wee confeſſe the ſame of theſe two gifts, in which the whole ſumme of our excellencie is plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted? <hi>To god and the Father,</hi> Thus expound it, To God which is the Father of Chriſt. For it is not lawful vnto vs to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge anye other God, but him that hath ſhewed forth himſelfe vnto vs in his Sonne. And this is the Raye which alone doth o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen the gate vnto vs if we will come vnto the true God. For euen therefore he is a father vnto vs, becauſe he hath embraced vs in his only begotten Sonne, and in him hath ſet forth his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therlye fauour to be viewed of vs. <hi>Alwayes for you.</hi> Some doe thus expound it, We giue thankes vnto God alwayes for you, that is to ſaye continually, And ſome thus, Praying for you al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes. It may alſo be thus expounded, As ofte as wee praye for you wee doe withall giue thankes vnto GOD. But this is the playner and more ſimple meaning, Wee giue thankes to
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:7610:8"/> God, &amp; withal we pray. Whereby he declareth, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the ſtate of the faithfull is neuer ſo perfect in this worlde, but that at all tymes ſomewhat is amiſſe or wanting. For euen hee who hath very well begon may euery day reuolte or fall a hundred times: and of neceſſitie we muſt continually go forward, whileſt as yet we be on our iourney. So than muſt wee minde ioying for gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces receiued, and for the ſame giue God thanks, that withal we deſire of him perſeuering and increaſe.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4 Hauing heard our faith.)</hi> This was a prouocation both of loue towards them, and of care for their ſaluation, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he heard that they excelled in faith &amp; loue. And certainly ſuch force ought the excellent gifes of God to worke in vs, that whereſoeuer they appeare, they ſhould enforce vs to be in loue with them. He cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth it faith <hi>In Chriſt,</hi> to the end we ſhould alway reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber, that Chriſt is the proper or very marke (for the leuell) of faith. He putteth <hi>Charitie to the Saints,</hi> not to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> end he would exclude or ſhut out other (therefrom), but for that as euery one is neere ioi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnto vs in God, ſo more neerelye ought we to embrace him with a peculiar loue. True loue than will extende it ſelfe to all men vniuerſally, becauſe euen all men are our fleſh, and are cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated after the Image of God: but as concearning degrees, it will begin at them that be of houſholde the of fayth.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <hi>5 For the hope layd vp for you in the heauens.)</hi> Neuer will the hope of eternall life bee idle in vs, but will bring forth in vs loue. For needes muſt it be that he, who is certainly perſwaded that the treaſure of life is layde vp for him in heauen, will ſette naught by the world, and will haue a longing thether. The me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditating vpon the heauenly life forceth oure affections both to ſerue God and to ſeeke after loue. The ſophiſters abuſe this te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonie or place to extoll the merits of workes, as though the hope of ſaluation depended vpon works: but their reaſon is fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolous. For it follow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th not, that hope is therefore grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded on workes, becauſe it pricketh vs vp to deſire to liue well: wheras nothing is more effectuous thervnto, than the free goodneſſe of God, which bring al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> confidence of works to naught. But there is a <hi>Met<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nya</hi> in the word <hi>hope:</hi> becauſe it is taken for the thing he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>tofor For hope in our harts is the glory which wee hope for in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But yet wheras he ſaith, That we haue hope
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:7610:9"/> layde vp in heauen, he meaneth that the faithfull ought to be as ſure of the promiſe of euerlaſting felicity, as if they had already a treaſure laide vp in a certaine and ſure place. <hi>Of whiche you haue heard before.</hi> Becauſe eternall ſaluation is a thing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue the capacitie of our vnderſtanding: therefore hee addeth, that the certaintie thereof was brought vnto the Coloſſians by the Goſpell. and withall he ſheweth them aforehande that hee will bring no new thing: but only that he meaneth this, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme them in that doctrine which they haue already receaued. Eraſmus hath tranſlated [it thus] <hi>the true word of the Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell.</hi> Neither am I ignoraunt, that, after the maner of the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewes, the Genitiue caſe is often vſed in Paule in place of the Epithet or Adiectiue: but here the wordes of Paule haue a greater Emphaſis or force. For in the toppe or higheſt degree he nameth the Goſpell, the <hi>word of truth,</hi> for honoures ſake: whereby they might the more ſurely and firmelye abide in the reuelation taken from it. And ſo the word Goſpell is ioyned ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitiuely.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <hi>6 As alſo in the whole world it doth fructifie.)</hi> This auay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth as well to the confirmation as to the comfort of the godlye, to ſee farre and wide the effect of the Goſpell, in gathering ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny vnto Chriſt. In deede the fayth thereof dependeth not vppon the ſucceſſe thereof, ſo that therefore we ſhould beleeue, becauſe many beleeue. Although the whole worlde ſhrinke, although heauen it ſelfe fall, yet the conſcience of a godly man ought not to wauer: becauſe God notwithſtanding, in whome the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience is grounded, abideth true. But this letteth not but that our fayth may be helped, as ofte as it ſeeth the power of God: which doth ſo much the more mightily ſhew forth it ſelfe, as the number is greater that is gayned vnto Chriſt. Adde this too, that in the multitude of the beleeuers at that time was ſeene the fulfilling of ſo many propheſies, which ſtretch out the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God from the eaſt to the Weſt. Is this a ſmall matter, or a vulgare and common helpe vnto fayth, with the eyes to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde fulfilled, concearning the kingdome of Chriſt to be exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded throughout all countreyes, that whiche the Prophets long afore had foretold? that which I ſay, there is none of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full but by experience doth fynde it himſelfe. Paule therefore
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:7610:9"/> with this ſentence would more enbolden the Coloſſians: that ſeing in all places the fruite and encreaſing of the Goſpell, they mighte with the more ioyous zeale. embrace it. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which I haue traunſlated, <hi>is encreaſed,</hi> is not reade in ſome co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies: yet becauſe it was ſomewhat ſit vnto the texte, I woulde not omit it. And it appeareth by the Commentaries of the olde Writers that this reading was alwayes more vſed. <hi>From the daye that you heard and knew the grace.</hi>) A praiſe of their aptneſſe, in that they did by and by embrace wholſome doctrine: a prayſe of conſtancie, in that they did abide in the ſame. And properly is the faith of the Goſpell called the knowledge of the grace of God: becauſe no man at any time hath taſted the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell but hee that knew himſelfe reconciled vnto God, and toke holde of ſaluation profered in Chriſt. <hi>In the truth,</hi> ſignifieth truely and without deceite. for as afore he teſtified, the Goſpell to be the vndoubted truth: ſo now he addeth, that it was ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely deliuered vnto them: and that of Epaphras. For where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as all doe boaſt (of) the Goſpell, but manye are euill Worke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, by whoſe eyther ignoraunce, or ambition, or auarice, the puritie therrof is corrupted, very requiſite it is to make a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betweene faythful and truſtie miniſters and thoſe that are naught. Neither yet is it ynough, to holde the name of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell: except we know that this is the true Goſpell, whiche is preached by Paule and Epaphras. Wherefore Paule by (gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing) his voice confirmeth the doctrine of Epaphras: to the end he may holde them in the ſame, and by that meanes mighte call tham back fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> varlets, who went about to bring in ſtrange doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trines. And withal he ſetteth out Epaphras himſelfe with a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table title, whereby he may haue the more authoritie. Finallye he maketh that he is the better beloued vnto the Coloſſians, in that hee ſayth hee teſtified vnto him their loue. Paule in euerye place is diligent in this, to make ſuch as he knew faythfullye to ſerue Chriſt, by his commendation to bee moſt deare vnto the Congregations: as on the contrary ſide, the miniſters of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than are wholy occupied in this, to alienate &amp; eſtrange by their ſiniſter ſpeeches the hartes of the ſimple from their faithful Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtours. <hi>Loue in the ſpirite.</hi> I take for ſpirituall loue as doeth
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:7610:10"/> Chriſoſtome: vnto whome I conſent not in that which wente before. Finally ſpirituall loue is that, which hath no reſpect to the world:<note place="margin">Is appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to be directed by Godlineſſe.</note> but it is conſecrate to the guidaunce and diſpoſition of godlyneſſe, and hath as it were a roote within, whereas car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall friendſhip dependeth of outward cauſe.</p>
            <q>
               <p n="9">9 We therefore alſo ſince the day we heard (thereof), ceaſe not to pray for you, and to deſire that you maye be fulfilled with the knowledge of his will, in all wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and ſpirituall prudence:</p>
               <p n="10">10 That you may walke worthie of God into al obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, bringing forth fruite in euery good worke, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing in the knowledge of God.</p>
               <p n="11">11 Strengthened with al ſtrength, according to the power of his glory, into al long ſuffering. and patience with ioy.</p>
            </q>
            <p n="9">
               <hi>9 We therefore alſo.)</hi> As afore in his gratulation he declared his loue towarde them: ſo doth he the ſame nowe in his earneſt prayer for them. And certenly as in euery one the grace of God is more apparaunt: ſo peculiarly ought we to embrace and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence them, and be carefull for their ſaluation. And what doth he wiſh vnto them? That they maye knowe God more fullye. whereby hee ſheweth, that ſomewhat is as yet wanting vnto them, that hee may make a waye for him to enſtructe them, and win them to heare him teache (the truth) more amply. for they that thinke they haue obtayned whatſoeuer is worth the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, doe deſpiſe and diſdaine whatſoeuer elſe is broughte them. He taketh therefore this perſwaſion away from the Coloſſians, leſt it ſhould be to them a let that they ſhould not willingly goe forward, and ſuffer to be perfected and amended that which was begon in them. But what knowledge doth he wiſhe vnto them? forſooth the knowlege Of the will of GOD. wherewith hee ouerthroweth all the inuentions of men and all thoſe ſpeculati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that are contrary to the worde of GOD. for the will of GOD is not to bee ſoughte elſe where than in his Worde. He ioyneth, <hi>in all Wiſedome,</hi> whereby he declareth that that
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:7610:10"/> will of God whereof he made mention is the onely rule of being rightly wiſe. For whatſoeuer he is that ſimplye deſireth to knowe thoſe thinges whiche it hath pleaſed God to reueale, he it is that knoweth what it is rightlye to be wiſe: and if wee deſire further, that ſhall be nothing elſe but to bee vnwiſe as not content with the meane. By the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which I haue: tranſlated, Prudence, I meane iudging or diſcerning whiche ſpringeth from the vnderſtanding. Paule calleth both of them ſpiritual: becauſe we atchieue them no otherwiſe but by the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the Spirite. For the naturall man perceiueth not thoſe thinges that are of God. <hi>1.</hi> Cor. <hi>2.14.</hi> As long as men are led by the ſence of their fleſh, they haue in deede their own wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, but ſuch (wiſedome) as is mere vanitie, howſoeuer elſe they flatter themſelues in it. We ſee what manner of diuinitie there is in the Papacie, what the bookes of Philoſophers con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne, what wiſedome it is that prophane or Godleſſe men haue in price. But lette vs haue in mynde, that that wiſedome alone which Paule commendeth and ſetteth out, is limitted in the will of God.</p>
            <p n="10">
               <hi>10 That you walke worthily in God.</hi> Firſt he teacheth what the end of ſpirituall vnderſtanding is, and to what purpoſe wee muſt profite in the ſchoole of God: namely that we liue worthy of God, that is, that it may appeare in our life, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we haue not in vayne bene taught of God. Whoſoeuer they bee that leuell not their ſtudies to this marke, it may be that they labour and take great paynes, but they doe nothing but wander by by wayes, and loſe their labour. Moreouer he admoniſheth, that this prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipallye is to be done of vs, if we will walk worthy of God, that we direct the whole courſe of our life after the will of God, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing our owne ſence and witte, and bidding all the affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of our owne fleſh farewell. Which alſo agayne hee confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth when he addeth (theſe wordes) <hi>into all obedience,</hi> or (as commonly they ſay) <hi>thorow pleaſing.</hi> Therfore if it be deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded what life it is that is worthy of GOD: this diffinition of Paul muſt alwaies be holden, namely that y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is it which leauing the rules &amp; ordinances of men, finally leauing the wit &amp; diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the whole fleſh, is ordred after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> obedience of God alone, Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hence enſue good works: which fruits God requireth of vs
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:7610:11"/> 
               <hi>Encreaſing in the knowledge of God:)</hi> He doth again repeat, that they are not ſo far come on, but that they haue neede of new encreaſements, with which admonition he prepareth them, &amp; as it were leadeth them by the hand to the deſire of going forward: whereby they may ſhewe themſelues readie to heare and apt to be taught. And that which is here ſpoken vnto the Coloſſia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, let al the faithful take it as ſpoken vnto them: and hereof let them collect this common exhortation, We muſt alwayes encreaſe in the doctrine of Godlyneſſe, euen till our dying day.</p>
            <p n="11">
               <hi>11 Strengthned with all ſtrength.</hi> As afore he wiſhed vnto them both ſound vnderſtanding &amp; the right vſe thereof: ſo nowe alſo he wiſheth vnto them a hart and conſtancie. By this means he admoniſheth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of their weakeneſſe &amp; imbicilitie, for that he denieth they can be ſtrong, but by the helpe of the Lord. neither doth he that only, but to the end he may the more amplifie &amp; ſee out this grace, he addeth (theſe wordes) <hi>According to his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious power,</hi> as if he ſhould ſay, ſo far off is it that any man by means of his own power can ſtand, but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the power of God muſt wonderouſly ſhew forth it ſelf, by helpiyg our infirmitie. Laſtly he teacheth in what thing the ſtrength of the faithfull ought to ſhew forth it ſelf, namely <hi>in al patience &amp; long ſuffering.</hi> For both co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually are they excerciſed vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croſſe in this world: &amp; a thouſand temptations do daily thruſt in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues to oppreſſe them: &amp; they ſee none of thoſe things which God hath promiſed. They muſt therfore arme themſelues with wonderful patience. that that ſaying in Eſa. <hi>30.15.</hi> may be fulfilled, <hi>Your ſtrength ſhalbe in hope &amp; ſilence,</hi> To ioine this peece, <hi>With ioye,</hi> vnto this ſentence is better (than otherwiſe) For although the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry reading is more often vſed with the Latines: yet the greeke copies agree rather vnto the reading (which I vſe): &amp; certainly pacience is not retained but by ioy: nor yet ſhall be ſtand with a ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g courage, who hath not a ioyfull liking of his own eſtate.</p>
            <q>
               <p n="12">12 Giuing thankes to God &amp; the Father who hath made vs meete to the pertaking of the inheritance of the Saints in light.</p>
               <p n="13">13 Which hath taken vs away out of the power of darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and hath ſet vs ouer into the kingdome of his
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:7610:11"/> beloued Sonne.</p>
               <p n="14">14 In whome we haue redemption by his blood, the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giueneſſe of ſinnes.</p>
               <p n="15">15 Who is the Image of the inuiſible God, the firſt begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten of all craatures.</p>
               <p n="16">16 Becauſe in him are created all thinges as well whiche are in heauen, as vpon the earth: viſible &amp; inuiſible: whether (they be) thrones, or dominations, or prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipalities, or powers.</p>
               <p n="17">17 All things are created by him, and into him: and he is before all things, and all thinges haue their being in him.</p>
            </q>
            <p n="12">
               <hi>12 Geuing thankes.)</hi> He returneth agayn vnto gratulation, that by this occaſion he may recken vp the benefites wherewith they are endowed by Chriſt, and ſo he entreth into a ful diſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Chriſt. For this was an only remedy for the Coloſſians, againſt all the deceits of the falſe Apoſtles wherewith they aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayed them fully to vnderſtand what Chriſt was. For whereof commeth it that we are caried about with ſo many kinde of doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trines, but becauſe we doe not throughlye knowe the power of Chriſt? For Chriſt alone cauſeth all other thinges ſodaynlye to vaniſhe. Therefore there is nothing that Sathan ſo greatly toileth about, as to caſt miſtes to darken Chriſt: becauſe hee knoweth that by this meanes the gate is opened to al lies. This than is the only way as well to retayne as to reſtore pure doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, to ſet Chriſt before the eyes what a one he is with all his goods and goodneſſe, that his power may be truely felt and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued. I ſpeake not here of the (bare) name. The Papiſtes doe commonly with vs confeſſe one Chriſt: how much ods is there the while betweene vs and them? namelye becauſe they while they confeſſe Chriſt to be the ſonne of God, by ſetting his power ouer vnto others, and by plucking it hither and thither, they almoſte leaue him naked and emptie. at the leaſte they robbe him of a greate parte of his glorye: ſo that hee is named the Sonne of GOD, but yet is not (in deede) ſuche an one as the Father would haue him to vs warde. And if ſo bee
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:7610:12"/> that the Papiſtes would with their hart receiue thoſe thinges which are contayned in this chapter, we and they ſhould by and by be at one: but the whole Papacie would fall, becauſe it ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth not but whereas Chriſt is not knowne. Whoſoeuer ſhall conſider and marke the ſtate and iſſue of this firſt chapter, will out of doubt acknowledge this (to be ſo). For nothing elſe is here handled, but that we ſhould know Chriſt to bee the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, the middeſt, and the end: that all thinges are to bee aſked of him: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> without him nothing is, nor can be found. Now there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore muſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> readers diligently and nighly mark w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> what colours Paule painteth out Chriſt vnto vs. <hi>Who hath made vs fit.</hi> As yet he ſpeaketh of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> father becauſe he is the beginning &amp; the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient cauſe (as they ſay) of our ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of God doth more expreſſe (his) maieſtie: ſo the name of Father (doth expreſſe his) clemency &amp; wel willing affection. It is meete that we ſhold behold both of theſe in God, that his maieſtie may ſtrike a feare and reuerence in vs, and that his fatherly loue maye procure a confidence &amp; a boldneſſe in vs. Therfore hath Paule not in vain ioyned theſe two together: if yet y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reading pleaſe you. which the Interpreter hath followed, vnto whom certaine very old greeke copies agree. Although there wilbe none abſurditie if we ſay he was content with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> word <hi>father</hi> (alone) Moreouer as it is need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full that his incomparable grace be expreſſed or declared vnder the name of <hi>Father:</hi> ſo alſo is it not leſſe needeful that we by the name of God ſhould be caried into the admiration and wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full liking of ſo great goodneſſe, for that he which is God hath ſo far abaſed himſelfe. For what benefit or good thing doth hee giue thanks vnto God? forſooth that he hath made him &amp; others meete to be partakers of the inheritance of Saints. For we are born the children of wrath, exiles, &amp; baniſhed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the kingdome of God: only it is the adoption of God, which maketh vs meete. And adoption dependeth vpon the free election. The Spirite of regeneration is the ſeale of adoption. He addeth <hi>in hight,</hi> that it might be an Antitheton or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary poſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> oppoſite &amp; ſet againſt the darkeneſſe of the kingdome of Sathan.</p>
            <p n="13">
               <hi>13 Which hath taken vs away.</hi> Beholde the beginning of our ſaluation, When God taketh vs out of the deepe pit of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction in which we are drowned. For where his grace is ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:7610:12"/> there is darkneſſe: as is read in Eſay <hi>60.2. Behold darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes ſhall couer the earth, and miſt the people: but vpon thee ſhall the Lord ariſe, and his glory ſhall be ſeene in thee.</hi> Firſt we our ſelues are called darkenes: and then all the whole world. And Sathan is the prince of darkenes, vnder whoſe tiranny we are helde in bondage, vntill we be ſet at libertie by the hande of Chriſte. Hereof gather, that the whole world, with the paynted wiſedome and righteouſneſſe therof, is in the ſight of God repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted nothing elſe but darkneſſe: becauſe there is no light without the kingdome of Chriſt. <hi>Hath ſet vs ouer into the kingdome,</hi> This is now the beginning of our happineſſe, when that we are ſette ouer into the kingdome of Chriſte: becauſe we paſſe from death into life. And this alſo doth Paule aſcribe to the grace of God: leſt any man ſhould think he could by his own force attain ſuch a good thing. As therfore our deliuerance fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bondage of ſin &amp; death is the work of God: euen ſo is our paſſing ouer into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kingdom of Chriſt. He calleth chriſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>Son of loue,</hi> or beloued of God y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Father: becauſe it is he alone in whome his ſoule deligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth as is in Mat. <hi>17.5.</hi> &amp; by whoſe means al other are beloued. For thus muſt we think, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ar not otherwiſe accepted of God but by Chriſt. And there is no doubt but Paule meant after a ſort to note the hoſtile enmity and diſſention that men haue with God, vntill the loue in the mediatour doth ſhine out.</p>
            <p n="14">
               <hi>14 In whom we &amp;c.</hi> Now doth he in order diſcourſe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all the partes of ſaluation are comprehended in Chriſt, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he alone, as he is of al things y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beginning &amp; end, ought to excell &amp; to be ſeene aboue all creatures. Firſt he ſayth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we haue in him redemptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: &amp; the ſame doth he by &amp; by interpret (to be) <hi>remiſsio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſins.</hi> For theſe ii. do appoſitiuely agree together. for certainly god in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he doth forgiue vs our ſins, deliuereth vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> guiltineſſe or daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of eternal death. This is our liberty, this is our boaſting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt death: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our ſins are not imputed vnto vs. He ſayth this redemptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is purchaſed by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <hi>blood of Chriſt:</hi> for by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacrifice of his death al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſins of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world are purged. Let vs reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber than y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> only price of reconcilement: &amp; therfore it is blaſphemie whatſoeuer it be y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Papiſts trifle concerning ſatiſfactions.</p>
            <p n="15">
               <hi>15 Which is the image &amp;c.</hi> He climeth higher, &amp; diſcourſeth of the glory of Chriſte. He calleth him y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Image of the inuiſible
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:7610:13"/> God, wherby he declareth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is he alone, by whom God, who otherwiſe is inuiſible, is manifeſted vnto vs: according to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, No man hath ſeene God at any time, the only begotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (ſon) who is in the boſome of the Father he hath manifeſted him vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, Ioh. <hi>1.18.</hi> I know after what maner the old writers are accuſtomed to expound (this place). for in that they were at vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunce &amp; controuerſie with the Arrians. they vrge the equalitie that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſon hath with the father,<note place="margin">Coeſſence and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie ſounde thus in en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh, to bee of the ſaye eſſence and ſubſtaunce.</note> &amp; the Coeſſence &amp; Conſubſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alitie: in the meane while they ſay nothing of that which is moſt principall: how the Father doth ſhew forth himſelfe in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sonne to be known vnto vs. That Chriſoſtome, hath placed his whole refuge in the word Image, whileſt he contendeth that the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture cannot be called the Image of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Creator: it is to weake. yea rather he is confuted of Paule whoſe words are, <hi>the man is the Image &amp; glory of God. 1.</hi> Cor. <hi>11.17.</hi> Leſt therfore we ſhould hold any thing but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which is firme, we muſt note, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the word I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage is not meant of the eſſence, but hath relation vnto vs. For therefore is Chriſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Image of God, becauſe he cauſeth God af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a ſort to be ſeene vnto vs although thereof alſo is gathered the coeſſence &amp; conſubſtanciallitie. For Chriſt ſhould not truly and in deede repreſent God, except he were the eſſentiall Word of God: ſeing that in this place he treateth not of thoſe thinges which by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municating or participating accord alſo to the cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atures: but he treateth of the perfect wiſedome, goodneſſe, righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe and powers of God: which to repreſent, no creature were of ſufficiencie. Ther ſhalbe than in this word a forcible weapon for vs againſt the Arrians: but yet we muſte beginne at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> relation which I haue ſpoken of, <hi>(viz)</hi> we muſt not ſtand in the only eſſence. The ſum is, that God in himſelfe, that is to ſay, in his naked maieſtie, is inuiſible: &amp; that not only vnto bodily eyes, but euen to the minds of men alſo: but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he is reuealed vnto vs in Chriſte alone, ſo that wee maye beholde him as it were in a glaſſe. For he doeth ſhew forth vnto vs in Chriſt, his righteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, goodneſſe, wiſedome, ſtrength and power, to be ſhorte him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe wholy &amp; totally we muſt take heede then y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſeeke it not elſe where: for whatſoeuer it is that ſhall without <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hriſt vaunt it ſelf by the name of God, it ſhalbe an idoll. <hi>The firſt begotten of al creatures.</hi> The reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> why he is thus called followeth by &amp; by: <hi>Becauſe in him all things are created,</hi> as in the third verſe
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:7610:13"/> following he is tearmed the firſt begotten of the dead, becauſe we all riſe agayne by him. Than he is not therefore only y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſte begotten, becauſe he went before all creatures in time, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he was begotten of the Father for this, that by him they ſhould be made. and he ſhould be as it were the ſubſtance or fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of all. The Arrians delt fooliſhlye, who reaſoned out of that, that he was therefore a creature. For it is not here tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, what he is in himſelfe: but what hee worketh or bringeth to paſſe in other.</p>
            <p n="16">
               <hi>16 Viſible and inuiſible.</hi> The former deuiſion of heauenlye and earthly thinges comprehended both theſe kindes. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he meant to auouche this principally of Angels, he nowe maketh mention of <hi>inuiſible thinges.</hi> That not onely the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly creatures which are manifeſt vnto the eyes, but alſo ſuch as are ſpirites, are made by the Sonne of God. And whereas followeth ſtraightwaye, <hi>Whether Thrones, &amp;c.</hi> it is as muche as if he ſhoulde ſaye, By what name ſoeuer they be called. By thrones ſome vnderſtande Aungels, but I think, that rather the heauenly palace of the maieſtie of GOD is [thereby] meant, which we muſt not dreame to be ſuch an one, as our mynd or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding may comprehende, but ſuche an one as is meete for God himſelfe. We ſee the ſunne &amp; moone, &amp; the whole orname<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the heauen: but the glory of the kingdome of God is hidden from our ſence and vnderſtanding, becauſe it is ſpirituall, and higher than the Heauens. To bee ſhorte, lette vs vnderſtande by Thrones that Seate of bleſſed immortalitie, which is exempte from all change and alteration. By the other names out of doubte hee meaneth the Angels. He calleth them Powers, Principallities, Dominations, or Lordſhips: not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they excerſiſe any regimente which is their owne, or elſe he indewed with force and ſtrength whiche properly belongeth to themſelues: but becauſe they are miniſters or ſeruauntes to execute Gods power and Domination. And it is often vſed, that as far as God doth extende &amp; put forth his force &amp; ſtrength in his creatures: ſo farre forth alſo doeth hee ſette ouer his names vnto them. And ſo hee alone is Lorde and Father: but they alſo are Fathers and lordes whom he vouchſaueth this honoure. And thereof it commeth that both Angels and Iudges
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:7610:14"/> are called Gods. Wherefore in this place alſo are Aungels ſet forth with great titles, which declare, not of what force they are by themſelues, or apart from God, but what God doth by them, and what functions and charge hee hath committed to them, Whiche thinges muſt ſo be taken, that nothing bee abated of the glorye of the only GOD. for hee doeth not ſo communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate and impart his force and ſtrength vnto the Aungels, that hee ſhould diminiſhe himſelfe: hee doeth not ſo worke by them, that he reſigneth or ſetteth ouer his power vnto them: hee will not haue his glory ſo ſhine in them, that it may be blemiſhed or darkened in himſelfe. Paule dothe purpoſedly ſo honourably ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toll the dignitie of the Aungels, leaſt any body ſhoulde thinke, that that were a let whereby Chriſt himſelfe ſhould be exalted aboue them. Therefore as by way of conceſſion or graunting he vſurpeth theſe names: as if he ſhould ſay, al their excellencie derogateth &amp; taketh awaye nothing from Chriſt, although they bee ſet out with notable titles. They that ſubtillie after a Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophicall maner doe deſcant in theſe wordes, to the ende they may pick out of them orders of Aungels, maye haue the fruiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and vſe of their liking, but certainlye they ſtraye farre from the mynd of Paule.</p>
            <p n="17">
               <hi>17 All things are created by him, and into him.)</hi> By foure reaſons he maketh the Aungels ſubiecte to Chriſt: <hi>(1)</hi> That they ſhould not darken his glorye, becauſe they were created by him. Secondlye, becauſe their creation ought to be referred vnto him, as vnto a legitimate ende. Thirdly, that hee was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes before they were created. Fourthly, for that hee ſuſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth them with his ſtrength, and preſerueth them in their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate. Although he affirmeth this not of them alone, but of the whole world alſo. So doth he place the ſonne of God in the higheſt ſeate of honour, that he may beare rule ouer both Aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels and men, and may bring vnder or into frame all the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures in heauen and in earth.</p>
            <q>
               <p n="18">18 And he is the ſeede of the body of the Churche, hee is the beginning, the firſte begotten from the dead: that he maye bee in all thinges holding the principalitie.</p>
               <p n="19">
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:7610:14"/>19 Becauſe it pleaſed (the Father) that al fulneſſe ſhould dwell in him.</p>
               <p n="20">20 And by him to reconcile all thinges vnto himſelfe, by pacifiing the row the blood of his Croſſe, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row him, as well thoſe thinges that are vppon the earth, as thoſe thinges which are in heauen.</p>
            </q>
            <p n="18">
               <hi>18 The hedde of the bodye.</hi> After that hee hath generallye diſcourſed touchinge the excellencie of Chriſte, and of his high principallitie ouer al creatures: he returneth agayn vnto thoſe things which peculiarly belong to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church. In the word Hed, ſome do conſider many things. And truly a litle after he wil vſe the fame Metaphor [I meane Hedde] in this ſence or meaning, that as head in the body of man is in ſteede of a roote, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whence the vitall power is diſpearſed into all the members: ſo doth the life of the Church proceede from Chriſt, &amp;c. But in this place he ſpeaketh, in my iudgement, chiefely of gouernment. He teacheth than that it is Chriſt alone, who hath power to gouern y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church to whome alone, the faithfull ought to haue reſpecte, of whome dependeth the vnitie of the bodye. The Papiſtes while they ſeeke to prooue the tyrannie of their Idoll, finde lackes that the Churche is headleſſe, vnleſſe the Pope as heade haue dominy-therin But Paul doth not yield this honor, no not to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Angels: and yet he maymes not the Church of her hedde: for that Chriſt, as he challengeth this title vnto himſelfe, ſo doth he veryly and in deede excerciſe the office thereof. Neither am I ignoraunt of their cauill wherewith they winde out themſelues, [which is this] The Pope is the miniſteriall hedde. but more ſplendent and noble is the name Hedde, than that it ought by any colour, to bee ſet ouer vnto anye mortall man, ſpeciallye withoute the commaundement of Chriſte. With more modeſtie behaueth Gregory himſelfe, who writeth that Peter in deede was a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal member of the church, yet y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he and the reſt of the Apoſtles, were members vnder our hedde <hi>Lib. 4. Epi. 92. <hi>He is the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning.</hi>
               </hi> Becauſe this word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> doeth ſomtime ſignifie, with the Greeke, the ende wherevnto all thinges are referred, wee mought in this ſence take Chriſte to be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, yet had I rather thus xpounde. Paules wordes, that he ſhoulde be the beginning
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:7610:15"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:7610:15"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:7610:16"/> becauſe he is the <hi>firſt begotten of the dead.</hi> for in the reſurrec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion he is the renuing and building vp of all thinges: and ſo the beginning of the ſecond and new creation, becauſe the firſt was fallen vtterly by the ruine and fal of the firſt man. Becauſe ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that Chriſt in riſing againe, hath begonne the kingdome of God, worthily is he called the beginning: becauſe then wee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to be in very deede in the preſence of GOD, when wee are renewed that we may be new creatures. <hi>Firſt begotten of the deade.</hi> Hee is ſo called, not onelye becauſe he didde firſte riſe agayne, but becauſe alſo hee reſtored other vnto lyfe. as <hi>1.</hi> Cor. <hi>15.20.</hi> he is called the firſte fruites of them that riſe agayne. <hi>That he may be in al thinges.</hi> Thereof he concludeth, that the primacy in all thinges accordeth and belongeth to him. for if he be the beginner and reſtorer of all thinges, it is manifeſt that of right this honoure is due vnto him. Although this peece <hi>In all,</hi> maye bee two wayes taken, <hi>(1)</hi> ether ouer all creatures, <hi>(1)</hi> or elſe in euery thing. But this ſkilles not much: becauſe ſimplye all thinges are broughte vnder his Dominion and rule.</p>
            <p n="19">
               <hi>19 Becauſe it pleaſed him.)</hi> To the end it may be the more firme which he hath preached touching Chriſt, nowe alſo he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, that it was ſo eſtabliſhed by the prouidence of GOD. And certaynly if we will reuerently adore this miſterye, neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarye it is, that wee ſhoulde bee called backe to that Well-ſpring. This, ſayth hee, is wroughte by the counſayle of GOD that all fulneſſe ſhould dwell in him. And hee vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandeth fulneſſe of righteouſneſſe, wiſdome, ſtrength or power, &amp; of al goodneſſe For whatſoeuer God hath, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hath he beſtowed vppon his Sonne, that hee mighte be glorified in him: as it is written Iohn <hi>5.20.</hi> And withall he admoniſheth, that whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer goodneſſe we require toward our ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, it muſt be drawn out of the fulneſſe of Chriſt: becauſe God hath thus determined, that he will no otherwiſe communicate or imparte himſelfe and his giftes vnto men, but by his Sonne. It is than as much as if he ſhould ſaye, Chriſt is to vs all thinges, and with out him wee haue nothing. Wherof it followeth, whoſoeuer derogate ought from Chriſt or miniſheth his power, or robbe him of his offices, or to be ſhorte pilfer awaye a droppe of his fulneſſe, they doe as
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:7610:16"/> much as in them lyeth, ſhake and hutle downe the eternal coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayle of God.</p>
            <p n="20">
               <hi>20 And by him to reconcile all things vnto himſelfe.</hi> This alſo is an honourable elogie or title of Chriſt, that we cannot o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe be ioyned vnto God but by him. Firſt let vs weigh, that our felicitie or happineſſe is planted in this, that we cleaue vnto God: agayne, that nothing is more miſerable than to bee alienated or eſtraunged from him. He pronounceth than, that we are by Chriſt alone happye, becauſe he is the hande that ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth God and vs together: agayne, that without him wee are moſt miſerable, becauſe we are ſhut out from God. As for that which he attributeth vnto Chriſt, lette vs remember that it is proper vnto him: ſo that no portion or peece of this praiſe muſt be aſcribed ouer vnto any other. Wherefore the Antitheſis or contraries muſt be vnderſtanded: if this bee the prerogatiue of Chriſt, it may not appertayne to others. For he manifeſtly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puteth agaynſte thoſe who deuiſed Aungels to bee pacifiers or peacemakers, by whiche an entraunce is made open vnto God. <hi>By pacifiing through the blood of his Croſſe.</hi> He ſpeaketh of the Father, for that he was made mercifull &amp; fauourable to his creatures by the blood of Chriſt. And he calleth it the blood of the Croſſe, becauſe therefore the blood of Chriſt was the guage and a price of our peacemaking with God, for that it was ſhead vpon the Croſſe. For the Sonne of God muſt haue bene a pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging or cleanſing ſacrifice, and paſſe vnder the guiltineſſe or daunger of ſinne, that we might be the righteouſneſſe of God in him. The blood of the croſſe than, ſignifieth the blood of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, which was offred vpon the croſſe to pacifie the wrath of God. While he addeth, <hi>By him,</hi> he meant not to ſpeake of anye new thing, but to expreſſe more certaynly that whiche alreadye he had ſayde, &amp; to imprint it as yet more deepely in our hartes: namely that Chriſt is ſo the only authour of reconcilement, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſhutteth out other meanes whatſoeuer. For no body elſe was crucified for vs. Than is it he alone by whome and by whoſe grace we haue God mercifull vnto vs. <hi>As wel which are vpon.</hi> If it like you to vnderſtand reaſonable creatures only, the ſame ſhall be men and Angels. Although it ſhall be now abſurditie to extend it to all without exception. but leaſt I ſhould he driue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:7610:17"/> reaſon the more Philoſophicallye, it liketh me that it beſpoken of men and Angels, and touching theſe there is no greate mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in it, to ſhew and proue that they haue neede of a peacemaker with God, But as concearning the Aungels, the queſtion is not eaſie to be vnfolded. For to what purpoſe is reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cileme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, where there was no diſſention or breache of loue? many being mooued with this reaſon, haue thus expounded this preſent place, The Angels were brought to agreement with men, and ſo the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly (creatures) were made friendes with the earthie. But the wordes of Paule ſound otherwiſe, (namely) <hi>that God hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled vnto himſelfe:</hi> that then is a forced ſolution. It re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth therfore that we ſee what maner of reconcilement that of Aungels and men is. I ſaye that men were reconciled vnto God, for that they were alienated from him before by ſinne, for that they were to feele him a Iudge to their deſtruction. vnleſſe the grace of a Mediator had come in the whileſt to pacifie his wrath. It was then a kind of pacifiing betweene God and men, for that by Chriſt enmitie was aboliſhed &amp; done away, &amp; ſo God of a Iudge is become a Father. Betweene God and the Angels the reaſon is far contrary: for among them there was no defect, no ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ne, and therefore no ſeparation. But yet for two cauſes the Angels alſo ought to be fet at peace with God. for ſeing they were creatures, they were not without daunger of falling, except they had bene made ſure by the grace of Chriſte. This is of no ſmall waight to continue in peace for euer with God, to haue a fixed and ſure eſtate in righteouſneſſe, that they neede not any more feare falling or defeating. Moreouer in this ſelfe ſame obedience which they performe to God, there is no ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite perfection, that they ſatiſfie God in euery behalfe, and without pardon. And to this purpoſe without doubte belongeth this ſentence in the booke of Iob, <hi>He ſhall find iniquitie in his Angels.</hi> for if it be expounded as ſpoken of the Deuill, what great thing is it? but the holy Ghoſt doth there pronounce the greateſt cleanneſſe and puritie to be foule &amp; filthie, if it be mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured according to the righteouſneſſe of God. We muſt then de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine, that there is not ſo much righteouſneſſe in the Angels, as is ſufficient to ioyne them fully and perfectly with God, and therfore they haue neede of a pacifier, by whoſe grace they may
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:7610:17"/> perpetually cleaue vnto God. Well therfore doth Paule, who denieth the grace of Chriſt to haue reſidence by abiding in men only, but maketh the ſame common vnto Angels alſo. neither is there any wrong done to the Angels, when they are ſent awaye to a Mediator, that by his benefite they may haue perfecte and firme peace with God. If any man vnder the pretence of the v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuerſall note <hi>(all)</hi> ſhal moue any queſtion touching the Deuils, whether Chriſt be their peacemaker alſo, I aunſwer that hee is not neither y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> peacemaker of wicked men. Although I confeſſe there is a difference, becauſe vnto wicked men is offred the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite of redemption, and ſo is it not to the Deuils. But this is nothing to Paules wordes, whiche contayne nothing elſe, but that it is Chriſt alone by whome all creatures, which haue any ioyning at all to God, cleaue vnto him.</p>
            <q>
               <p n="21">21 And you when ſometime you were eſtranged, and eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies by cogitation in euill workes.</p>
               <p n="22">22 Now hath he reconciled in the bodye of his fleſhe by death: that he might make you ſtand holy and vnre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proueable in his ſight.</p>
               <p n="23">23 If ſo be you abide grounded and firme in faith, and bee not remoued from the hope of the Goſpell whiche you haue heard: which is preached among all crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures which are vnder heauen: of which I Paule am made a Miniſter.</p>
            </q>
            <p n="21">
               <hi>21 And you, when ſometime.</hi> Now doth he ſhape vnto them a general doctrine by an <hi>Hypotheſis,</hi> that they may perceiue them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues guiltie of the greater vnthankfulneſſe if they ſuffer them<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelues to be lead ouer from Chriſt to new deuiſes and inuentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. and this order muſt dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly be marked: becauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> applicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (if I may ſo ſay) of peculiar or ſpeciall doctrine, doth more neerely touch y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> quick. Afterward he calleth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> back to experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they might acknowledge in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues the benefite of the redemption wherof he maketh me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tion, as if he ſhold ſay, you your ſelues ar a docume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t or example of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grace which I preach to be exhibited &amp; ſet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> vnto me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> through Chriſt. for <hi>ye wer eſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged,</hi> namely fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Ye were enemies,</hi> now ar ye receiued into fauor. &amp; whence
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:7610:18"/> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth that? forſooth for that God being pacified and appeaſed by the death of Chriſt, is agayn friendes with you. Although in this ſentence is the chaunging of the perſon, for that which hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto he hath taught touching the father, now he preacheth of Chriſt. for ſo of neceſſitie muſt it be expounded, becauſe he ſaith, in the body of his fleſh. I enterprete the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> [which is tranſlated <hi>cogitation</hi>] to be put to augme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t the matter, as if he ſhould haue ſayd, that they were vtterly and with all the whole ſence of their mynd eſtranged from God, leaſt any body ſhoulde philoſophically fain (this) eſtraunging to be in ſome part, as the Popiſh deuines reſtrain it to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> inferiour concupiſcences. Naye rather, ſaith Paul, becauſe it made you hatefull vnto God, it oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupied the whole mynde. To be briefe his mynde was to poynte forth man, altogether as he is, vtterly to diſagree fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God, &amp; to be vnto him an enemie. The olde Interpreter hath tranſlated, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ſence,</hi> Eraſmus hath tranſlated it <hi>minde,</hi> and I haue vſed the word <hi>cogitation,</hi> for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Frenchmen cal intent. For ſuch is the force of the greeke word, &amp; Pauls meaning doth ſo require it. Furthermore y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> word <hi>enemies,</hi> whereas it hath as well a paſſiue as actiue ſignificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, agreeth with vs iumply ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way as long as we be without Chriſt. for both are we born the children of wrath, and all the cogitations of the fleſh are ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred agaynſt God. <hi>In euill workes</hi> He proueth by the effects the inward hatred that lyeth hidden in the hart. For in that men co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to wipe themſelues cleane from all blame, ſo long till they be manifeſtlye conuinced; God euen ſheweth their impietie by their outward workes: as more largely is treated. Rom. <hi>1.19.</hi> Furthermore looke what we heare in this place of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Coloſſia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geth alſo vnto vs. for in na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ure we differ nothing. This on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ods there is, that ſome are called ſtraightway from their mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers wombe, whoſe wickedneſſe God preuenteth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they breake not forth into manifeſt fruits: others after they haue gon aſtray a good part of their life, are brought back again into the ſheepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold. Yet we all haue neede of Chriſt to be a pacifier becauſe we are the ſeruaunts of ſinne: and wheras ſinne is, there is enmity betweene God and men.</p>
            <p n="22">
               <hi>22 In the body of his fleſh.)</hi> A ſpeeche in kinde ſtraunge and abſurde: but <hi>the body of fleſh,</hi> is as much (as if he had ſayde)
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:7610:18"/> the humane body whiche the Sonne of God hath common with vs. His minde than was to declare that the Sonne of God hath put on the like nature that we haue, that is to ſaye, that he had taken on him a body that was baſe and lowlye, earthye and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dangered to many infirmities, that he might be our mediatour. When he addeth <hi>by death,</hi> he calleth vs back to the conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſacrifice. For the Sonne of God muſt become man, and partaker of our fleſh, that he might be our brother: by dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he muſt become a ſacrifice, that he might pacifie the Father vnto vs. <hi>That he might make you ſtande holy.</hi> The ſeconde principall part of our ſaluation, namely newneſſe of life. For in theſe two members or peeces cheefely conſiſteth the whole pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of redemption: <hi>viZ.</hi> in forgiueneſſe of ſinnes, and ſpirituall regeneration. Iere. <hi>31.33.</hi> That which already he ſayde, was a great matter, that righteouſneſſe was purchaſed vnto vs by the death of Chriſt, that ſinne being done away, we might be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable vnto God. But nowe hee teacheth that another thing commeth withall that is as notable, namelye the giuing of the holy Ghoſt, whereby we are newlye faſhioned after the Image of God. And it is a place worth the marking, that free righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe is not giuen vnto vs in Chriſte, vnleſſe we be borne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new alſo by the Spirite into the obedience of righteouſneſſe: as he teacheth <hi>1.</hi> Cor. <hi>1.30,</hi> that Chriſte is made vnto vs righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe and ſancrification. And wee obtayne righteouſneſſe by being freely accepted: but ſanctification we obtayne by the gift of the holy Ghoſt, while we become newe man. and of both theſe graces there is an vnſeperable knot. But let vs note that this holyneſſe is but begonne in vs onely, and that it doth dayly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite and go on: but that it ſhall not be perfect, vntill Chriſt ſhall appeare to the building vp of all thinges. For naughtilye and frowardly did the Celeſtines and Pelagians in time paſt abuſe this place, to exclude the grace of forgiueneſſe of ſinnes. For they did ſhyne a perfection in this world, which mought ſatiſfie the iudgemente of GOD, ſo that mercye ſhoulde be ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtuous and more than needes. But Paule doeth not here teache what is fulfilled in this Worlde: but what the ende of our vocation i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, &amp; what good things are brought vnto vs by Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="23">
               <hi>23 If you abide.)</hi> An exhortation to perſeuere, whereby hee
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:7610:19"/> admoniſheth that it ſhall be in vayne whatſoeuer grace hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to hath bene beſtowed vpon them, except they abide in the ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of the Goſpell. And ſo he ſignifieth that they are as yet but in their courſe, and haue not yet attained to the marke or goale. For euen then the ſtabilitie &amp; firmeneſſe of their fayth was in hazarde among them by meanes of the ſubtle dealings of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> falſe Apoſtles. and liuely &amp; conningly doth he paint forth vnto them the certaintie of faith, when he biddeth the Coloſſians to bee <hi>grounded and firme</hi> in the ſame. For faith is not like ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing or thinking, which is ſhake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with diuers &amp; ſundry motions: but it hath a firme ſtedfaſtneſſe and conſtancie, whiche reſiſteth and beateth back all the engines of the deuils. And therefore all the popiſh diuinitie will neuer giue no not ſo muche as a ſmall taſt of true fayth: which holdeth as a certain and approued rule, that we muſt always doubt as well of the preſent ſtate of grace, as that we ſhall perſeuere to the end. Afterward alſo hee noteth the relation which is betweene fayth and the Goſpell, where he ſayth that then the Coloſſians ſhall be firme in fayth, if they bee not made ſlip away from the hope of the Goſpell: that is to ſay which ſhineth vnto vs by meanes of the Goſpell. for where the Goſpell is, there is hope of eternall ſaluation. But let vs beare in mynde that the ſumme of all is contayned in Chriſt. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in this place he commaundeth to flie all doctrines whiche leade awaye from Chriſte, to the ende that the mindes of men may be occupied any where elſe. <hi>Which you haue heard.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the falſe Apoſtles alſo are accuſtomed proudly to boaſt the name of the Goſpell, who rent and teare Chriſt in peeces: (and this is a conning of Sathan often vſed, falſlye vnder the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of the Goſpell to trouble the conſciences, that the truth of the Goſpell may be confuſed): therfore by name doth Paule a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouche that this Goſpel which the Coloſſians had heard, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of Epaphras, is the naturall, true, and vndoubted Goſpel, left they ſhould open their cares to contrary doctrines. He addeth moreouer a confirmation, that it is the ſame that is preached o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer all the world. This is, I ſay, no vulgar or common confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, when they heare that they haue the whole vniuerſall Church ageeing with them: and that they follow not any other
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:7610:19"/> kinde of doctrine, than which the Apoſtles haue in like manner raught, and is euery where receaued. Ridiculous iwis is the boaſting of the Papiſtes, in that with this argument or reaſon they impugne our doctrine, becauſe it is not allowed and ratifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed euery where to be preached, (and) becauſe we haue fewe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting to it. For if they would burſte, they ſhall neuer take this from vs, (namelye) that we at this daye deliuer no other thing than that was preached afortime by the Prophets and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, and obediently receiued of the whole company of ſaints. Neither meant Paule that the Goſpell ſhould be approued by the conſent of all tymes: ſo that if it were reiected or refuſed, the authoritie thereof ſhould ſtagger or be readye to fall. But he rather reſpected or conſidered that commaundement of Chriſt, Mar. <hi>16.15.</hi> Go ye, preache ye the Goſpell to euery creature, which dependeth of ſo many prophecies of the Prophets, which did denounce that the kingdom of Chriſt ſhould be ſpread into al the world. What other thing than meant Paule by theſe words than that the Coloſſians were alſo watered with thoſe liuing Waters, which ſpringing from Ieruſalem, ſhoulde ſlowe ouer all the Worlde? We alſo, and that not in vayne, nor without notable fruite and comforte, doe boaſt that we haue the ſelfe and ſame Goſpell, whiche by the Edicte and commaundemente of the Lord was preached amongeſt all peoples, whiche was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued of all Churches, in the profeſſion whereof haue liued and dyed all Godly perſons. Neyther is the conſent and agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Churche, whiche indeede is worthye ſo noble a Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, a vulgate and baſe helpe to defende vs agaynſt ſo many aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaultes. And willingly doe we ſubſcribe vnto Auguſtine, who with this argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t principally doth confute the Donatiſtes, for that they bring a Goſpell vnhearde of and vnknowne vnto all Churches, and truely it was deſeruinglye: for if it be a true Goſpell that is broughte in place, and the ſame not appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued nor ratified by anye Churche, it followeth that vayne and falſe are ſo manye promiſes, wherewith is foretolde that the preaching of the Goſpell ſhoulde be caried into the whole world: and which affirme that the ſonnes of God ſhal be gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red out of all peoples and countreys. &amp;c. But what doe the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtes? They bidding the Prophets and Apoſtles farwell, and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:7610:20"/> paſſing ouer the olde Church, will haue their defeating or fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling away from the Goſpel be taken for the conſent of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Church. what is like this? Therefore when we reaſon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the conſent of the Church, let vs returne vnto the Apoſtles and their preaching: as Paule here doeth. But leſt any take too ſtraightly the vniuerſall note <hi>[all];</hi> Paule meaneth no other thing than that the Goſpell was preached here and there farre and wide. <hi>Of which I am made.</hi> He ſpeaketh alſo of his owne perſon, which was very needefull. for we muſt alwayes take heede, that wee doe not raſhlye thruſt in our ſelues into the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of teaching. Therefore doth he teſtifie that the office was inioyned him, that he might procure vnto himſelfe righte and authoritie And ſurelye he doeth ſo ioyne his Apoſtleſhip with their faith that they cannot refuſe his doctrin, but by forſaking the Goſpell which they haue embraced.</p>
            <q>
               <p n="24">24 Now reioyce I in ſufferinges for you, and I fulfill thoſe thinges that wante in the affections of Chriſte in my fleſhe, for his bodye whiche is the Church.</p>
               <p n="25">25 Wherof I am made a Miniſter, according to the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of God, which is giuen me toward you, to fulfill the word of God.</p>
               <p n="26">26 A miſtery hidden from the beginning of tymes and generations, whiche nowe is reuealed vnto his Saints.</p>
               <p n="27">27 Vnto whome God would make knowne what the riches of the glory of this miſterie in the Gentils is, whiche is, Chriſte in you, the hope of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye.</p>
               <p n="26">26 Whome wee preache, warning euery man, and tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching euerye manne in all wiſedome, that wee maye make ſtande euery man perfecte in Chriſte Ieſus.</p>
               <p n="29">29 To which thing I alſo labour, ſtriuing according to his power, which worketh in me mightily.</p>
            </q>
            <p n="24">
               <hi>24 Now reioyce.)</hi> Before hee challenged authority vnto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:7610:20"/> by meanes of his calling: but nowe hee vſeth preuention, leſt the bandes and perſecutions which he ſuſtained for the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, ſhould miniſhe any thing of the honour of his Apoſtleſhip. for Sathan euen abuſeth theſe occaſions alſo, to make the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntes of God leſſe ſet by. Beſide that he enboldeneth them by his example, that they ſhould not be feared with perſecutions: and he commendeth and ſetteth out his zeale, that he may be of the more authoritie. Moreouer he doth with no baſe token make knowne his loue toward them, whiles he affirmeth that he wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly abideth for their ſakes the afflictions which he ſuffceth. But ſome man will ſay, whereof ariſeth this ioy? Forſooth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he did ſee fruite comming thereof. as if he ſhould ſay, The affliction for you is pleaſaunt vnto me: becauſe I ſuffer it not in vayne. As in the firſt Epiſtle to the Theſſalonians, <hi>3.6.7</hi> he ſayth he reioyceth in all neceſſitie and affliction, for their fayth which he heard of, <hi>I fulfill thoſe thinges that are wanting:</hi> I take the copulatiue to be put for the cauſall. for he yieldeth a reaſon, why he is ioyous while he ſuffreth: <hi>viz.</hi> becauſe hee is a partner therein with Chriſt, and nothing can be wiſhed more bleſſed then this partnerſhip. And hee ſetteth downe a common conſolation to all the godly, that in all ſorrowes and troubles, and ſpecially if they abide any greefe for the Goſpell, they are partakers of the croſſe of Chriſt, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they may enioye the fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of the bleſſed reſurrection. Moreouer hee doth affirme that ſo are fulfilled the things that are wanting in the afflictions of Chriſt. for as he ſpeaketh Ro. <hi>8.29.</hi> whome God hath elected, thoſe alſo hath he predeſtinated, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they might be made like faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned to y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Image of Chriſt: to th'end he might be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt begotten among the brethren. Beſide that we know that the vnitie of the hedde and members is ſo great, that the name, of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> doeth ſomewhile comprehend the whole body. As in the firſt Epiſtle to the Corinthians. cap. <hi>12.</hi> verſe. <hi>12.</hi> for whereas hee in that place had ſpeeche concearning the Churche, in the ende he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludeth that the matter is in Chriſt as it is in a mans body. As therefore Chriſt hath once ſuffered in his owne perſon, ſo doeth he dayly ſuffer in his members: and by this meanes are fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the paſſions and ſufferings, which the father by his decree &amp; purpoſe hath alotted for his bodye [to ſuffer]. The ſeconde
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:7610:21"/> thinking hereof which ought to vpholde and comfort our harts in afflictions, [is] that it is ſo determined and appoynted by the prouidence of God, that wee beare a figure of Chriſt in bearing the croſſe and ſuffering affliction, and that the communicating, or partaking which we haue with him, might ſtretche out it ſelf to this poynt alſo. He addeth alſo the thyrd reaſon, namelye that his ſuffringes are fruiteful, &amp; that not to a few only, but to the whole Church. Before he ſayd he ſuffred for the Coloſſians. nowe hee auoucheth more, <hi>viZ.</hi> that the profite thereof reacheth to the whole Church. Of which profite or fruite is ſayde Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lippians cap. <hi>1.12.</hi> What is more cleare than this expoſition, what is leſſe forced and more playne? That Paule therefore is ioyous in perſecution, becauſe he conſidereth as elſe where hee writeth, that the mortification of Chriſt is to be caryed aboute in our body, that his life may be made manifeſt in vs. Alſo vnto Timothie, If wee ſuffer with him: we ſhall alſo raigne with him: if we dye with him, we ſhall alſo liue with him: our ende than ſhall be happy and glorious. Secondly, that condition of ſtate is not to be refuſed which God hath ordained to his church that the members of Chriſt maye haue an agreeable likeneſſe and proportion with their head. Thirdly, that afflictions are willingly to be ſuffred, as being profitable vnto all the Godlye, and which doe further the ſaluation of the Churche, by ſetting forth the doctrine of the Goſpell. But all theſe thinges ſette at naught and not regarded, the Papiſtes haue coyned a newe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe, whereby they mighte proue their indulgences &amp; pardons. They call Indulgences the forgiueneſſe of ſinnes whiche wee haue by the merites of Martyrs. For whereas they denye the forgiueneſſe of ſins to be free, but faine the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be redeemed with ſatiſfactorie works: whereas (now) ſatiſfactions be not ſo many as they ſhould be, they call for helpe the blood of Martyrs, that it may auayle in the ſighte of GOD to purge and clenſe with Chriſtes blood. And this mixture they call the Treaſure of the Churche: the Kayes whereof afterwarde they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitte to whome it liketh them. Neyther are they aſhamed to the mayntenaunce of ſo curſed a blaſphemie, to wreſt this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent place, as though Paule ſhould here auouche his ſufferings to bee auaileable to purge and waſhe awaye the ſinnes of men.
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:7610:21"/> They vrge the worde, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>afflictions,</hi> as though Paul denied thoſe things which Chriſt hath ſuffred to be ſufficient to the redemption of men. But there is no man that ſeeth not, that Paule ſo ſpeaketh, becauſe by the afflictions of the godly the body of the Church muſte be brought to her perfection, while the members are made like faſhioned vnto their heade. And I ſhould bee afraide to be ſuſpected to ſlaunder in rehearſinge ſuche monſtrous matters, were it not that their owne bookes bee witneſſes, that I charge them with nothinge falſelye. They vrge this alſo, that Paule ſayth hee ſuffereth for the Churches. It is a wonder, that none of the olde Fathers once thought vppon this ſharpe and ſubtill ſence or expoſition. For they all expound it as we doe, That the ſaints ſuffer for the Church, becauſe they confirm the faith of the Church. But the Papiſts gather thereof that the Saints are redeemers, becauſe they ſhed their blood to waſhe awaye ſinnes. But to the ende the readers maye throughly ſee their impudencie and ſhameleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: I graunt that as well the martyrs ſuffred for the church as Chriſt did, but after diuerſe wayes: which I had rather expreſſe by Auguſtines wordes than by myne owne. For thus he writeth in the <hi>84.</hi> treatiſe vpon Iohn, Although bretheren we die for the bretheren: yet no blood of a Martir is ſhedde for the remiſſion of ſinnes: which Chriſt hath done for vs. neither hath hee in this pointe ſeete forth vnto vs, what wee ſhoulde followe, but for what we ſhould reioyce. Alſo in the fourth Booke to Bonifacius, As alone the Sonne of God was made the ſonne of man that hee might make vs the ſonnes of God: ſo alſo hee alone tooke for vs puniſhemente without faulte, that through him without deſerte wee mighte obtaine grace that was not our due. Vnto which ſayings, that of Leo the Biſhop of Rome is like, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> iuſt haue taken or receaued Crowns, but haue not geuen any: and of the fortitude of the faythfull are ſprong examples of pacience, and not giftes of righteouſnes. For why their deathes were ſingular, neyther doeth any man paye anothers debte with his ende. That this ſence is in Paules words, is eaſilye apparant by the text for he ioyneth by &amp; by after, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſuffreth according to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diſpenſation co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him. And we know that the miniſterie not of redeeming, but
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:7610:22"/> of edifieng the Church was committed vnto him, and he doeth playnely by and by confeſſe the ſame. And that is it alſo that that he writeth to Timothie <hi>2.</hi> Epiſtle and <hi>2.</hi> Chap. verſe <hi>10,</hi> that he abideth all thinges for the elects ſake, that they may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine ſaluation which is in Chriſt Ieſus. And <hi>2.</hi> Corinth. <hi>1.4.</hi> that he ſuffereth all things willingly for their comforte and ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation. Let the godly readers than learn to hate and deteſt theſe prophane ſophiſters, who to the ende they maye ſmothe on a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour vppon their fayned deuyſes, doe ſo notorioulye corrupt the Scriptures and falſifie them.</p>
            <p n="25">
               <hi>25 Whereof I am made a Miniſter.</hi> Loe, in what reſpect hee ſuffereth for the Church: namely becauſe he is a miniſter, not to giue the price of redemption (as Auguſtine ſkilfully and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lily doth ſpeake it) but to preache. Furthermore otherwiſe doth he now call himſelfe a Miniſter of the Church, than he doeth <hi>1.</hi> Cor <hi>2.4.</hi> call himſelfe the Miniſter of God, and a little before [the miniſter] of the Goſpell. For the Apoſtles ſerue God and Chriſt to promote the glory of them both: they ſerue the Church for the ſaluation thereof, and miniſter the Goſpell it ſelfe. The reaſon of the Miniſterie therefore is diuerſe in thoſe kindes of ſpeakings: but the one of them cannot ſtand without the other. And he ſayth, <hi>toward you;</hi> that they may know that the charge thereof belongeth alſo vnto him. <hi>To fulfill the word.</hi> Hee ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the ende or finall cauſe of his miniſterie: that the word of God might be effectuous, which is done while it is obedientlye receaued. For this is the ſtrength of the Goſpell: that it may be the power of God into ſaluation to euerye one that beleeueth, Rom. <hi>1.16.</hi> God therfore by his Apoſtles giueth vnto his word force and effect. For although the preaching it ſelfe, whatſoeuer the happ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be, is the fulfilling of the word: yet the fruite at laſte doeth ſhew, that the ſeede was not caſte abroade in vaine.</p>
            <p n="26">
               <hi>26 A miſterie hidden.</hi> A commendation of the Goſpell, that it is a wonderfull ſecret of God. Not without cauſe doth Paule ſo often extoll the Goſpell with as great praiſes as he maye. for he ſawe it was to the Iewes a ſtombling blocke, to the Greekes foliſheneſſe <hi>1</hi> Cor. <hi>1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1.</hi> And we alſo at this daye doe ſee howe greatly it is hated of hypocrites, howe proudely it is di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>piſed of the world. Paule therefore to the ende hee maye ouerthrowe ſo
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:7610:22"/> wrongfull and peruerſe iudgements, doth honourably extol the dignitie of the Goſpell, as often as occaſion ſuffereth him, and to that purpoſe he vſeth diuers arguments according to the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtaunce of the place. here he calleth it an high or loftie ſecret which was vnknown from times and generations: that is to ſay from the beginning of the world by ſo many circuites &amp; turns of ages. And that he ſpeaketh of the Goſpel appeareth. Ro. <hi>16.25.</hi> Ephe. <hi>3.9.</hi> and ſuch like places. But the reaſon why it is ſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, is demaunded. Some iudge, becauſe Paule toucheth by name the calling of the Gentils, that this is the only reaſon why it is ſo called. for that the Lord, as it were vnhoped for, hath poured out his grace vppon the Gentils, whome hee ſeemed to haue depriued for euer of the fellowſhip and partaking of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life. But to him that looketh nighly vpon al thinges, it ſhal appeare that this is a third reaſon, and not the only reaſon: as touching this preſent place, and that other to the Romanes, which I haue cited. For the firſt reaſon is, that whereas God had gouerned his Church before the comming of Chriſt, vnder obſcure and darke coueringes, as well of wordes as of ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, he ſodaynly ſhineth out with great cleareneſſe by the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of the Goſpell. The ſeconde is, that whereas before, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing was ſeene but outwarde figures, Chriſt was exhibited bringing with him the full truth, vnder whiche he was hidden. The third is that which I ſpake of, that all the whole Worlde which hitherto was eſtraunged from God, ſhould be called into the hope of ſaluation, and vnto all ſhould be offred like inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce of eternall life. The attentiue conſideration of theſe thinges ſhall conſtrayne vs to honour and reuerence this miſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie which Paule preacheth: although it be contemptuouſly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded of the world, or elſe laughed at. <hi>Which now is reueled.</hi> Leaſt that any man ſhould draw this worde <hi>Miſterie,</hi> to anye o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther meaning, as though he ſpake as yet of a thing hidden in a corner, or vnknown, he now at laſt addeth that it was publiſhed, to the end it ſhoulde be knowne to men. That therefore whiche by the nature thereof was a ſecret, was by the will of God made open and manifeſt. Wherefore there is no cauſe that the obſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie or darkeneſſe thereof ſhould feare vs, ſeing God hath reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led it. He addeth, <hi>to the Saints,</hi> becauſe the arme of Lord is not
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:7610:23"/> reuealed vnto all, that they may vnderſtand his counſayle.</p>
            <p n="27">
               <hi>27 Vnto whom God would.</hi> Here he brideleth the boldneſſe of men, that they ſuffer not themſelues to be more wiſe or elſe to ſearche after more than they ought: but that they learn to be content with this one thing, <hi>viZ.</hi> ſo it pleaſed God. For the will of GOD ought to be ynough, and ynough vnto vs a cauſe ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fici<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nt. yet this is principally ſpoken to commende the grace of God: becauſe Paule meaneth, that men in no wiſe did miniſter cauſe vnto God that they ſhould be partakers of this ſecrete, while he teacheth that of his own accord he was moued herevn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, and becauſe he would. For it is a common thing in Paule, to ſette the good pleaſure of God oppoſite and agaynſte all the merites and outwarde cauſes of men. <hi>What the riches are.</hi> Wee muſt alwayes marke how highly he ſpeaketh aboute ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolling the dignitie of the Goſpell. for he knewe the vnthank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe of men to be ſuch, that they would for all this ſecurelye contemne, or at the leaſt ſet little by, this ineſtimable treaſure and farre paſſing grace of God. And therefore not being content with the worde <hi>Myſtery,</hi> he addeth <hi>glory,</hi> and the ſame not ſmall or common. for what was more wonderfull, than that the Gentils, who ſo many yeres were drowned in death, that they might ſeeme almoſt paſt hope, ſodaynlye ſhoulde be reckoned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the children of God, and receaue the inheritaunce of ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? <hi>Wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch is Chriſt in you,</hi> That whiche in generalitie hee had ſayde of the Gentils, hee now applieth euen to the Coloſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, that they may in themſelues acknowledge more effectuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye, and embrace with the greate reuerence the grace of God. He ſayth than, <hi>Which is Chriſt;</hi> whereby he meaneth that all that ſecrete is contayned in Chriſte: and that all the riches of the heauenly wiſedome are obtayned when wee haue Chriſte: as more playnly he will a while after affirme. He addeth, <hi>In you:</hi> becauſe now they poſſeſſe Chriſt, from whome a late they were ſo eſtraunged as nothing could be more. Laſtly hee calleth Chriſt the <hi>hope of glory:</hi> that they may know that they wante nothing to full and perfect bleſſedneſſe after that they haue ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned Chriſt. And this a wonderfull worke of GOD, that in earthen and frayle veſſels, ſhoulde abide the hope of heauenl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> glory.</p>
            <p n="28">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:7610:23"/>
               <hi>28 Whome we preache.)</hi> In this place doth hee ſet ouer and apply to his preaching, whatſoeuer afore hee hath vttered tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the wonderfull and honourable ſecrete of God: and ſo he expoundeth that which already hee had touched as concearning the diſpenſation committed vnto him. For this is his purpoſe that he may ſet forth and garniſhe his Apoſtleſhip, &amp; that he may procure authoritie to his doctrine. For after that he had highly extolled y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Goſpell, now he addeth, that that which he preacheth is a diuine ſecrete. But not without cauſe did he of late put in, that Chriſt is the ſumme of that ſecrete: to the ende they maye know that nothing can be more fully and perfectly taught than Chriſt. The wordes which follow, haue alſo great waight. Hee maketh himſelfe a teacher of all men: whereby he meaneth that none excell ſo highly in wiſedome, that they ought to exempte themſelues from taking him to bee their mayſter: as if hee ſhoulde ſaye, The Lorde hath appoynted me in a high place a publique Preacher of his ſecrete, that all the worlde without exception might learne of me.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In all wiſedome,</hi> is as much as if he ſhould vphold his doctrin to be ſuch, as might bring a man to firme and perfect wiſdome, and ſuch as ſhould want nothing. And that is it which by and by he addeth, whoſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uer they be that ſhew the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues true diſciples, they ſhall be made perfect. Loke the <hi>2.</hi> cha. to the Cor. <hi>1.</hi> Epiſt. And what can we require that is better than this, that hee yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vnto vs very high perfection. He repeateth, <hi>In Chriſt,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, that they ſhoulde haue no will to knowe any thing ſauing Chriſt alone. Out of this place alſo maye wee gather a definiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of true wiſedome: namelye as by whiche wee are made to ſtande perfect in the ſight of God: and that in Chriſt, and not elſe where.</p>
            <p n="27">
               <hi>27 To which thing.)</hi> With two ſentences he augmenteth the glory of his Apoſtleſhip, and his doctrine. Firſte hee maketh mention of his earneſt mynde: whiche is a token of difficultye. For ſuch thinkes for the moſt parte are moſt excellent which are moſt hard &amp; vneaſie [to be atchieued]. The other is more firme, <hi>viz.</hi> in that he reckeneth the power of God, to ſhine forth in his miniſterie But he ſpeaketh not of the ſucceſſe of his preaching only, (although therein alſo appeareth the bleſſing of God) but
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:7610:24"/> alſo of the efficacie of the holy Ghoſt, in which God didde ſhew himſelfe euidently. For iuſtly doth hee aſcribe his indeauoures and laboures, when as he ſurmounted the meaſure [or abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie] of man, vnto the power of God, which he affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to be ſeene to worke mightily in this behalfe.</p>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ The ſecond Chapter.</head>
               <q>
                  <p n="1">1 And I will haue you know howe great a contention I haue for you, &amp; them which are at Laodicia, and whoſoeuer haue not ſeene my face in the fleſh.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 That their harts may receiue comfort when they are knitte together in loue, and into all the riches of the certaintie of vnderſtanding, into the knowe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the miſterie of God, and of the Father, and of Chriſt.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 In whome are hidden all the treaſures of wiſedome and vnderſtanding.</p>
                  <p n="4">4 And this ſay I vnto you, leaſt any body ſhould deceiue you with perſwading ſpeeche.</p>
                  <p n="5">5 For although I am abſent in bodie, yet in ſpirite am I with you, reioycing and ſeing your order, and the ſtedfaſtneſſe of your fayth in Chriſt.</p>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>AND I will haue you know.)</hi> He teſtifieth his loue towarde them, to the ende he maye haue the more credit and authoritie. for willinglye doe we beleue thoſe whom we know to be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for our ſaluation. Neyther is it a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon or vulgare ſigne of loue for that hee was carefull for them in the middeſt of death: that is to ſaye, when hee was in hazarde of his life. And to the ende he maye the more ſet forth the vehemencie of his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence and care, he calleth it a Contention or Strife. I repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t Eraſmus for that he hath tranſlated it Care or Care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe: and yet the force of the Greeke Verbe is to bee noted:
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:7610:24"/> becauſe <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> is put, whereas there is contention or reſiſting. With the ſame reaſon he confirmeth, his miniſterie to belong vnto them. for from whence came ſo earneſt a cogitation or min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of their ſaluation, but becauſe the Apoſtle of the Gentils ought with loue and care to embrace yea euen thoſe whome hee knew not? And becauſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly there is no loue amongſt thoſe that are not acquaynted, he abaſeth the knowledge that is got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by ſight, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſayth, <hi>Whoſoeuer haue not ſeene my face in the fleſh,</hi> For among the ſeruaunts of God there is another ſight, than is that which is of the fleſh, which winneth loue. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is almoſt by common conſent alowed of, that the firſt E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle to Timothie was written from Laodicia: therfore certaine alot this Laodicia, wherof Paule maketh mention, vnto Gala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia: wheras that other was the metropolitan or mother citie of Phrigya Paratiana. But vnto me it ſeemeth more likely to bee true, that that is a corrupt &amp; faultie inſcription: as in his place ſhalbe noted.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2 That their hartes may receiue comfort.</hi> Now he declareth what he wiſheth vnto them: and he ſheweth an affeccion which is truely Apoſtolique. For he affirmeth that none other thing is ſo deare vnto him, as that they be knit together in faith and loue. He ſheweth therefore that hee was moued with no prepo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterous deſire, (as in ſome it happeneth) to take vppon him ſo great care for the Coloſſians and others: but for that the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of his office did ſo require. <hi>Comfort</hi> is taken in this place for the true quietneſſe and tranquilitie wherein they reſt or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe themſelues. He affirmeth that than at laſt they ſhall obtain the ſame, <hi>if they be knit together in loue</hi> and fayth. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by appeareth where <hi>ſummum bonum</hi> the cheefeſt felicitie is to be placed, and in what things it conſiſteth: namely while wee agreeing together into one faith, may be alſo ioyned together in mutuall charitie: this I ſay is the perfect ioy of a Godly hart: that is the bleſſed life. And as charitie or loue is here commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of the effect, in that it ſheaddeth true ioy into the myndes of the godly: ſo agayn the cauſe thereof is ſhewed, where he ſaith. <hi>Into all fulneſſe of vnderſtanding.</hi> For this is the bonde of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vanitie, euen the truth of God, while we embrace y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame with one conſent. For peace &amp; concorde with men floweth out of that
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:7610:25"/> fountayn. <hi>The riches of the certaintie of vnderſtanding.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe moſt men being content with a ſmall taſte, haue nothing but a confuſed and vaniſhing knowledge, he doth by name ſette downe the riches of vnderſtanding: by which worde he meaneth a full and pithie vnderſtanding and perceauing. and withall he admoniſheth, that according to the meaſure of vnderſtanding, we muſt profite and goe forwarde in loue and charitie. By the worde, <hi>certaintie,</hi> he ſheweth the difference betweene faith, and thinking or ſuppoſing. For he truely and in deede doeth knowe God, that wauereth not or ſtaggereth not by doubting: but that abideth in a ſtedfaſt and conſtant perſwaſion. Paule calleth this conſtancie and ſtedfaſtneſſe oft time <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: whiche worde alſo hee vſeth here in this place, and ioineth it continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally with fayth: ſo that certaynlie it can no more bee plucked away from it, then heate or lighte canne bee from the Sunne. Deuiliſhe than is the opinion and doctrine of the Schoolemen, for that, in taking awaye <hi>certaintie,</hi> they put in place thereof a morall coniecture (as they tearme it). <hi>Into the knowledge of the miſterie.</hi> This peece is to be read appoſitiuely for he expou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth what that knowledge is wherof he maketh mention: name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye that it is no other thing but the knowledge of the Goſpell. For the falſe Apoſtles alſo doe ſet out their deceites with the ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of wiſedome. but Paule retaineth the Children of God with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in (the compaſſe) of the Goſpell alone: that they maye deſire to know nothing elſe. Why he vſeth the worde <hi>Myſterie</hi> for the Goſpell is alreadye ſayde. But hereof let vs learne that the Goſpell can be receiued, by faith alone, and not by reaſon, nor yet by the thorow ſight of mans mynd or vnderſtanding: becauſe otherwiſe it is a thing hidden from vs. I interprete <hi>Myſterie of God,</hi> paſſiuely, as in which God reuealed. For ſtraight after he ioyneth, <hi>And of the Father, and of Chriſt,</hi> with which peece he meaneth that God cannot be knowne, but in Chriſt, as agayne the Father muſt needes be knowne, where Chriſt is knowne. for Iohn affirmeth both, He that hath the Sonne hath y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Father alſo, he that hath not the Sonne, hath not the Father neyther. Therefore whoſoeuer think they know any thing of God with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Chriſt, they forge to themſelues an Idoll in ſteed of God. As alſo on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary ſide he knoweth not Chriſt, who is not brought
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:7610:25"/> vnto him by the father, and ſo embraceth whole God in him. It is the while a place worthy to be thought on to proue the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head of Chriſt, and that he is of one eſſence with God. For after he hath ſpoken afore of the knowledge of God, he doth by and by applye it as well to the Sonne as to the Father. whereof it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth, that the Sonne is God equall with the Father.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3 In whom are,</hi> or, <hi>In which are,</hi> The peece <hi>in quo</hi> (which may be engliſhed <hi>in whome</hi> or elſe <hi>in which</hi>) either hath relation vnto all that which is comprehended, touching the knowledge of the myſterie; or elſe to that only which went next before, that is, Chriſt. Although there is ſmall difference betweene the one and the other, yet the latter liketh me better, and is more al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed and vſed. The ſence is than, that in Chriſte lie hidden all the Treaſures of Wiſedome and knowledge. whereby he decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth that we are perfectly wiſe, if we know Chriſt truely: in ſo muche that it is madneſſe, to wiſhe to knowe any thing ſauing him. For ſeeing that the Father hath made manifeſt himſelfe wholy in him: he meaneth to be wiſe without God, which is not content with Chriſt alone. If it like you to expounde it of the Myſterie, the meaning ſhalbe, that all the wiſedome of the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhall be included in the Goſpel, whereby God is reuealed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs in his Sonne. And he ſaith that the <hi>treaſures are hidden,</hi> becauſe they appeare not out to be ſeene in great glittering and gallant ſhewe, but they lye as it were hidden rather vnder the humilitie and baſeneſſe of the croſſe, and vnder ſimplicity which is contemptible. For the preaching of the croſſe (as we haue it to the Corinthians) is alwayes fooliſhneſſe vnto the world. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene Wiſedome and Vnderſtanding in this place I put no great difference, becauſe doubling of a thing ſo muche auayleth to augment the matter, as if he ſhould haue ſayde there can bee founde elſe where no iote of knowledge, inſtruction, learning, or wiſedome.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <hi>4 This I ſay leaſt any body.</hi> Becauſe the deuiſes &amp; inuentions of men (as afterwarde we ſhall ſee) haue a ſhew or kynde of wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, the myndes of the Godlye muſt bee preuented by this per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion that the onelye knowledge of Chriſt is ynough and y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough. And ſurely this is the Ray which maye lock vp the gate agaynſte all wicked erroures. For what was the cauſe
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:7610:26"/> that men wrapped themſelues in ſo many vngodly opinyons, in ſo many idolatries, in ſo many foliſh ſpeculations, but becauſe they deſpiſed the ſimplicitie of the Goſpell, and were bold to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire higher? Whatſoeuer errours than is in the papacie, they maye thanke this vngratefulneſſe of it, that being not content with Chriſt alone, they gaue themſelues to ſtraunge doctrines. Well therefore doth the Apoſtle to the Hebrewes, while hee minded to exhort the faythfull that they ſhould not ſuffer them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to be carried away with ſtraunge or new doctrines, vſe this foundation firſte of all, Chriſt yeſterday, and to daye, and for euer. with whiche worde hee ſignifieth that they are out of daunger who abide in Chriſt and that they are laide open to all deceites and ſubtelties, which thinke not Chriſt ſufficient. So Paule here willeth, that whoſoeuer he is that will not be decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, muſt be armed with that principle, (namely) It is not law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for a Chriſtian man, to ſauour any thing but Chriſt. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though whatſoeuer ſhall be broughte afterwarde haue neuer ſo bewetifull a coloure, yet nothing will bee done, it ſhall worke nothing. To bee briefe there ſhall be no likelyhoode nor perſwading ſpeeche which ſhall bende but euen the bredth of a finger the heartes of them who haue addicted their myndes to Chriſte. A place truely to be commended highly. for as he hath preuented or ſtopped all wicked opinyons and doctrines, who hath taught men to know nothing beſide Chriſt; ſo the ſame is the waye, whereby we may at this daye deſtroy and hurle down the whole Papacie, as that which euidently appeareth compact and made out of the ignoraunce of Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <hi>5 For although in body I am abſent, yet in ſpirite am I with you.</hi> Leſt any man ſhould obiect, that warning or admoniſhing were ſkant ſeaſonable from a place ſo farre diſtaunt, hee ſayeth that his loue towarde them cauſeth that hee is preſente with them in ſpirite, and iudgeth, as it were of the preſente caſe, what is expedient for them. And by prayſing the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate they preſentlye were in, hee warneth them that they ſlyde not nor bende therefrom. <hi>Reioyſing,</hi> ſayeth hee, <hi>and ſeeing,</hi> that is to ſaye, becauſe I ſee. For the copulatiue hath the force of a cauſall, whiche is muche vſed of the Latines
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:7610:26"/> and Greekes. It is as much as if he ſhould ſaye, Go on as you haue begon, for I know that hitherto you haue healde a righte courſe, for the diſtaunce of the place letteth not that I ſhould not ſee you with the eyes of my minde. <hi>Your order and ſtedfaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</hi> He putteth two thinges, in which conſiſteth the perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Church, <hi>viZ.</hi> order amongſt themſelues, and fayth in Chriſt. Signifiing by order as well conſent, as, well ordred ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and the whole diſcipline. He praiſeth their fayth by their conſtancie and ſtedfaſtneſſe, declaring that it is a vayne ſhadow of fayth, whereas the mind wauereth and altereth betweene di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe opinions.</p>
               <q>
                  <p n="6">6 As therfore ye haue taken on you Chriſt Ieſus the Lord, walke ye in him.</p>
                  <p n="7">7 Rooted in him, and builte, and confirmed in fayth, as ye are taught, abounding in the ſame with thankes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing.</p>
               </q>
               <p n="6">
                  <hi>6 As.)</hi> Vnto prayſe he ioyneth exhortation, in which he tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth that it will nothing profite them that they haue once re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued Chriſt, except they abide continuallye in him. Further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more in that the falſe Apoſtles alleage the name of Chriſte, to deceaue and beguile: he twiſe preuenteth this danger while he biddeth them go forwarde as they had bene taught, and as they had receaued Chriſt. For with theſe wordes he admoniſheth, that ſo conſtantly muſt they ſtick to the doctrine whiche Epa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phras deliuered and they embraced, that they take heede to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues for (admitting) any other doctrine &amp; fayth. As Eſay ſaid, chap. <hi>30.21.</hi> This is the way, walke in it. And truelye ſo muſt we vſe the matter that the truth of the Goſpell, after it is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted vnto vs, muſt be vnto vs a braſen wall, to fende of all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceites. And with three Metaphors, doth he ſet out what maner conſtancie of fayth he requireth of them. The firſt is in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worde <hi>Walke.</hi> For he compareth the pure doctrine of the Goſpell, as they learned it, to a certayne and playne way: which whoſoeuer keepeth, ſhall be out of daunger of error and going awrie. He exhorteth them then if they wil not go out of the way, that they turne not out of the courſe or walke which they haue begonne.
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:7610:27"/> The ſecond met<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>phor is taken of trees. for as a tree ſpreading his rootes deape in the ground hath ſuſtentation and defence y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to abide all the forces of windes and ſtormes: ſo if any bee fixed in Chriſt deepely and thorowly, as in a ſtrong rote, he can by no ſubtill deuiſes of Sathan bee hurled downe from a right ſtate. Contrarywiſe if any doe not groundfaſte his rootes in Chriſt, hee will eaſily be caried about with euerye blaſt of doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, no otherwiſe than a tree that is defenced with no rootes, at the firſt blaſt is turned vp. The third metaphor is of building. for an houſe which is not ſupported with a foundation, will quicklye fall. The like happeneth to them who leane vpon other ſhores then Chriſt: or elſe who are not ſtronglye founded in him, but haue the houſe of their faith as it were doubtfull and hanging by meanes of their weakeneſſe and lyghtneſſe. Theſe two things are to be marked in the words of the Apoſtell: <hi>viz.</hi> that the firmenes of them who reſt vpon Chriſt muſte be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moueable: and theire courſe or proceeding neuer a whit doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, or endangered vnto error. and this is an excellent prayſe of faythe by the effecte. Secondlye, ſo long muſte we profite in Chriſt, as vntill wee haue taken deepe rooting in him. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of we maye gather readyly, that they doe onely goe aſtraye by by wayes and are diſquieted hither and thether, that hold not Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="7">
                  <hi>7 And confirmed in faith.</hi> He repeateth the ſelfe ſame with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out figure, whith he had ſpoken by metaphors: namely the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge forward on the way, the defencing of the roote, and ſhoring or vpholding of the foundation, to be the firmenes and conſtancy of fayth. And note, in that they were well taught, this reaſon was ſet forth vnto them, to the ende that ſafely and ſurely they might faſten their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oote in that fayth which they had tried. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounding.</hi> He wil not onely haue them ſtand vnmoueable, but encreaſe euery day more and more. Whereas he addeth, <hi>With thankes giuing,</hi> he will alwayes haue them myndfull whence faith it ſelfe commeth: that they be not puffed vp with arrogan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, but rather that they repoſe themſelues with feare in the gift of God. And certainly vnthankfulneſſe is very ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in fault, why the light of the Goſpel, as alſo other the graces of God are taken from vs.</p>
               <q>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:7610:27"/>
                  <p n="8">8 Tak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eede leaſt any robbe you through Philoſophy and vayne deceite, after the tradition of men, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the elements of the world, &amp; not after Chriſt.</p>
                  <p n="9">9 Becauſe in him dwelleth all the fulneſſe of the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head bodily.</p>
                  <p n="10">10 And ye are fulfilled in him, who is the heade of all principalitie and power:</p>
                  <p n="11">11 In whome ye are alſo circumciſed with Circumciſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on not made with hand by putting off the body of the ſinnes of the fleſh, by Circumciſion I ſay of Chriſt.</p>
                  <p n="12">12 Being buried together with him by Baptiſme: in whom alſo ye are riſen by the faith of the efficacie of God, who hath raiſed him from the dead.</p>
               </q>
               <p n="8">
                  <hi>8 Take heede leſt any.</hi> Agayn it teacheth them againſt what poyſon the preſeruatiue which he gaue them ought to be taken. For although that [I meane a firme fayth] be a common reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die agaynſt all the deceites of the deuill, as I haue ſayd: yet had it at that time a peculiar vſe among the Coloſſians, vnto which it ought to be applyed. Take heede, ſaith he, leſt any robbe you. He vſeth a very fit tearm. for he alludeth vnto theeues, who whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they cannot viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly ſteale the whole flock, than do they by ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tletie driue away ſome of the Cattel. So maketh he the church Chriſts ſheepefolde, and the hurdles or cloſures hereof, the pure doctrine of the Goſpell. Vs than that are the ſheepe of Chriſte, he declareth to reſt in ſafetie, as long as wee holde the vnitie of fayth, and he maketh the falſe Apoſtles like to Theeues whiche carye vs awaye from the foldes. Wilt thou then be reckoned in the flock of Chriſt, wilte thou abide in his foldes? bende not the bredth of a nayle from the puritie of doctrine. For vndoubtedlye Chriſt will doe the duetie of a good Paſtor Sheaphearde with ſhielding vs, if we will heare his voyce only, and refuſe the voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of others. To be breefe, the <hi>10.</hi> chapter of Iohn, is an expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this preſent place. <hi>By Philoſophie.</hi> Becauſe many haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> lye thoughte that Paule in this place doeth condemne Philoſophie, it muſt be defined what he meaneth therby. In my
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:7610:28"/> iudgement he vnderſtandeth, whatſoeuer men do inuent of their own heads, while they will haue a ſmack of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ir <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ne ſence: and that not withoute ſome fayre pretence or colour of reaſon, that in ſhew it may be propable. For there is not much adoe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout reiecting the inuentions of men, when they haue no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation or ſetting out: but aboute them that deceiue the myndes with a deceitful opinion of wiſedome. Or if any had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther haue it ſpoken at a word, Philoſophie is nothing elſe but a perſwading maner of ſpeech, which inſinuateth or ſhouldreth in it ſelfe by fayre and plauſible reaſons into the myndes of men. Such I graunt ſhal all the ſlie reaſons of Philoſophers bee, if they put too ought of their owne to the pure word of God. there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Philoſophie ſhalbe no other thing but a corrupting of pure doctrine, if it be mingled with Chriſt. But let vs bere in mynde that Paule vnder the name of Philoſophy, hath onlye condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned all forged doctrines, which ſpring out of mans brayn, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer colour or ſhew of reaſon (beſides) they haue. That which followeth next of <hi>vaine deceit,</hi> I doe thus interprete, Beware of Philoſophie, which is nothing elſe but a vayn deceyte. <hi>After the tradition of men.</hi> He doth more nighly ſhewe what Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophie he miſliketh: and alſo in two reſpects he reproueth it of vanitie: becauſe it is not according to Chriſt, but according to the rules of men, and is placed in the elementes of the Worlde Note that hee ſetteth Chriſte oppoſite and agaynſte both the Elementes of the Worlde, and alſo the Traditions of men. whereby hee meaneth, that whatſoeuer is forged in the brayne of man, is not agreeable vnto Chriſt, who is appoynted to vs an only Teacher from the Father, to retayne vs in the ſimplicitie of the Goſpell. And that (ſimplicitie) is cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted euen with a little leauen of mans traditions. He mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth in like manner that all thoſe doctrines are contrarye vnto Chriſt which place in the elements of the worlde the worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of God, which we know by the rule of Chriſt to be ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all: which doctrines alſo entangle the minds of men with thoſe trifles and toyes, whereas Chriſt calleth vs ſtraight vnto him. But what calleth he <hi>Elements of the world?</hi> no doubt but hee calleth ceremonies ſo. for by and by after for an Example hee bringeth forth one kinde of them, namely Circumciſion. And
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:7610:28"/> why he ſo calleth them, two reaſons are vſuallye brought. ſome thinke it to bee a Metaphor: ſo that elemenets are rudimentes meete for Children, which bring not to perfection of doctrine. ſome take them in a proper ſignificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or meaning for outward thinges and ſuch ss are ſubiect to corruption, which ſerue no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to the kingdome of God. the former expoſition doth more like me as alſo Galat. <hi>4.3.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="9">
                  <hi>9 Becauſe in him dwelleth.</hi> The reaſon why thoſe elements of the worlde, whiche are the traditions of men, agree not with Chriſt. for they are additions to ſupply defect or want, as they ſay. But in Chriſt is perfection, to which nothing can be added. Therefore whatſoeuer men mingle in of their own heades, it fighteth with the nature of Chriſt becauſe it condemneth him of imperfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and inſufficiencie This argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t alone is ynough to confute all the fained deuiſes of the papiſtes. For to what end belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g they but to make vp &amp; bring to perfection, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon in Chriſt? but this reproch agaynſt Chriſt is not to be born. They ſaye in deede that they adde nothing to Chriſt: becauſe they (I meane elements) are a peece of Chriſtianitie which they haue tied or patched to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Goſpell. but they eſcape not with that kynde of Cauill. For Paule ſpeaketh not of an imagined Chriſt but of a Chriſt preached, who hath reuealed himſelfe by a certayne and ſure doctrine. Furthermore where he ſayth that, <hi>The fulneſſe of the Godhed dwelleth in Chriſte,</hi> he meaneth no other thing but that God wholy is founde in him: ſo that he, longeth after a thing that is better and more excellent than God, who is not content with Chriſt alone. The ſumme is that God hath exhibited himſelfe vnto vs in Chriſt fully and wholy. The interpreters doe ſundrye wayes expounde the Aduerbe, <hi>bodily.</hi> I doubt not but that it is put vnproperlye, for ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiallie. for he ſetteth oppoſite this manifeſtation which we haue in Chriſt, vnto all other manifeſtations y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euer were. For God hath often exhibited himſelfe vnto men, but that in part (one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye). but in Chriſt he wholye communicateth himſelfe vnto vs. Otherwhere alſo he hath manifeſted himſelfe, but in figures, or power and grace. but in Chriſte hee hath eſſentiallye appeared vnto vs. So is fulfilled that, <hi>1.</hi> Iohn <hi>2.23.</hi> Hee that hath the Sonne, hath alſo the Father. For they haue God truly preſent,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:7610:29"/> &amp; altogether haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fruitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of him, who haue Chriſt in profeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
               <p n="10">
                  <hi>10 And ye are fulfilled in him.</hi> He addeth that that perfect eſſence of the Godhead which is in Chriſt, in this reſpecte doth auayle vs, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſhould be alſo perfect in him: as if he ſhold ſay, Wheras God wholy hath his abiding in Chriſt, therefore it is [that he hath ſo], y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we obtaining him, may poſſeſſe in him a ful and ſure poſſeſſion. Therefore they doe double iniurie to God, who conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t not themſelues in Chriſt alone. for beſide y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> that they derogate from the glorie of God, by deſiring and ſeeking after ſomewhat aboue his perfection: they are alſo vnthankefull, in that they ſeeke elſe where y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which already they haue in Chriſt. Yet Paule meaneth not, that Chriſt his perfection is poured o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer into vs, but that it is in him wherwith we may be fulfilled, ſo that nothing any more ſhalbe lacking vnto vs. <hi>Which is the head.</hi> He hath againe put in this peece for cauſe of the Angels, meaning that the Angels alſo ſhalbe ours if we haue Chriſt. but hereof afterwarde. But in the meane while we muſt thinke on this, that we are vp and downe encloſed with grates, leſt our faith ſhould ſtep but euen a little aſide from Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="11">
                  <hi>11 In whome alſo ye are circumciſed.</hi> Hereof appeareth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he had controuerſie with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> falſe Apoſtles who mingled y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law with the Goſpell, and by that meanes they made Chriſt as it were hauing two ſhapes or faſhions. And he nameth one kynd for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample ſake. He proueth the Moſaicall circumciſion not only ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous, but alſo quite contrarie to Chriſt, becauſe it deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the ſpirituall circumciſion of Chriſt. For to this ende was Circumciſion giuen vnto the fathers, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it mighte be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> figure of a thing abſent. they therefore that keepe ſtill y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> figure now that Chriſt is come, do denie y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> to be fulfilled which doth figure. Let vs reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber than y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> outward circumciſion is here compared with ſpirituall (circumciſion) no otherwiſe than the figure with the truth. A figure is of a thing abſent. it doth than put awaye the preſence of the very thing it ſelfe. This is it than that Paule contendeth for, becauſe in Chriſt is fulfilled that whiche was ſhadowed in circumciſion made with hand: (and) that now there is of the ſame neyther profite nor vſe. Than he pronounceth it to be the Circumciſion of Chriſt, which is made in the hart: and therfore that that outward circumciſion is not now in any wiſe
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:7610:29"/> required: becauſe that whereas the thing it ſelfe is extant, that ſhadowing ſigne vaniſheth, as hauing no place but where the thing it ſelfe is away. <hi>By putting of the body.</hi> He calleth that maſſe or lumpe, which is compact of all vices, a Body, by a fine Metaphor. For as we are cloſed about with our bodyes: ſo alſo are wee enwrapped on euery ſide with a ſtack or heape of vices. And as the body is framed and compact of diuers members, all and ſingular which haue their proper actions and offices: ſo out of that heape of corruption all ſinnes do poure out as mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers and partes of the whole. There is the like maner of ſpeeche Ro. <hi>6.13.</hi> He taketh fleſhe, after his manner for nature corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. The <hi>body of the ſinnes of the fleſh,</hi> than is the olde man with his workes. Only in the maner of ſpeaking there is a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitie: becauſe properly in this place he blaſeth out the maſſe of vices, which ſpring fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nature being corrupted. This he ſaith we obtayne by Chriſt, that regeneration wholy is his benefite. He it is that circumciſeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> foreſkin of our harte, that is, which mortifieth all the concupiſcences of the fleſh, not with his hande, but by his ſpirite. Therefore in him is extante and manifeſt the truth and very thing of the figure.</p>
               <p n="12">
                  <hi>12 Being buried with him by Baptiſme.</hi> Hee declareth as yet more plainly the manner of ſpirituall circumciſion. namely for that wee being buried with Chriſte, are pertakers of his death. Hee doeth by name teache that wee obtayne that by Baptiſme that it may the better appeare, that there is no vſe of Circumciſion vnder the kingdome of Chriſte. For ſome might elſe obiect, Why putteſt thou away Circumciſion vnder this pretence, becauſe the effecte thereof is in Chriſte? <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiection. </seg>
                  </label> was not Abraham circumciſed alſo ſpirituallye? and yet this lec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted not but that he ſhould adde a ſigne to the thing? outwarde Circumciſion therefore is not ſuperfluous, although the inwarde (Circumciſion) be geuen by Chriſt. <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>
                  </label> Paule preuenteth ſuche manner of obiection, by making mention of Baptiſme. Chriſt, ſayth he, worketh in vs ſpirituall Circumciſion, that old ſign which was in force vnder Moſes not comming in place, but Baptiſme. Baptiſme than is the ſigne of the thing exhibited and plainly ſet out which Circumciſion did figure while it was ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſente and awaye. It is an argument taken of the gouernment
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:7610:30"/> which God hath ordayned. for they that hold ſtill circumciſion, deuiſe a way of diſpenſation and gouernmente cleane contrarye to that which God hath appointed. In that he ſaith, We are bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried with Chriſt, is more than to be cruci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ed (with him). for burying ſetteth out a perpetuall progreſſe or continuaunce of mortification. Whereas he teacheth this is done by Baptiſme, as alſo he doth, Rom. <hi>6 4.</hi> he ſpeaketh as he is wont, attributing efficacie to the Sacrament, left in vayne it ſhoulde ſignifie that which is not. By Baptiſme than we are buried with Chriſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Chriſt doth therewithall effectually performe mortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which in Baptiſme he ſignifieth: that the thing maye bee ioyned with the ſigne. <hi>In whome ye haue alſo riſen.</hi> He ampli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth the grace which we obtaine in Chriſt, which goeth farre before circumciſion. Wee are not onely grafted into the death of Chriſt, ſayth he, but we riſe agayne alſo in newneſſe of life. wherefore the more iniurious are they againſt Chriſt, which aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay to bring vs agayne to Circumciſion. And he addeth, <hi>By the faith.</hi> for verily by it we take hold of that which is offred vnto vs in Baptiſme. But what fayth? (forſooth) of his Efficacie or working. whereby he meaneth that fayth hath here foundation in the power of GOD. But becauſe Fayth rometh nor ſtraieth not about in a confuſed and (as they ſaye) an indefinite contemplation of the power of God: he ſetteth out what efficacie they ought to reſpect, namely that wherewith he hath raiſed vp Chriſt from the dead. And he taketh it as graunted; becauſe it is vnpoſſible that the faithfull ſhould be pulled away from their hedde, that that power which hath ſhewed forth it ſelf in Chriſt, ſhould in like maner be proued out vpon them all.</p>
               <q>
                  <p n="13">13 And ye when ye were dead by ſinnes, and in the vncir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion of the fleſh, hath hee together quickned with him, by forgiuing you al your ſinnes.</p>
                  <p n="14">14 And hauing put out the handwriting in decrees which was agaynſt vs, which was contrary to vs, and that hath he taken out of the way being faſtened to the Croſſe.</p>
                  <p n="15">15 Spoyling principalities and powers hath led the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> along openly, triumphing ouer them in it.</p>
               </q>
               <p n="13">
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:7610:30"/>
                  <hi>13 And ye when ye were dedde.</hi> That whiche in generall wiſe he hath diſcourſed, he admoniſhed the Coloſſians, to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider in themſelues: which is a very effectuall maner of teaching. Fardermore ſeing they were Gentils when they were conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto Chriſt, he therby warneth them how ſtrang a thing it were to ſkippe ouer from Chriſt to the ceremonies of Moſes. <hi>Ye were,</hi> ſayth he, <hi>dead in vncircumciſion.</hi> This word may be taken ether in a proper ſignification or elſe metaphorically. if you take it properly, the ſence ſhall be, <hi>Vncircumciſion</hi> is a ſymboll or badge of eſtrangement from God, for where the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenaunt of grace is not, there is vncleanneſſe, and thereof com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth the curſe and damnation. But God hath called you from vncircumciſion to himſelfe: and therfore from death. So ſhould he make vncircumciſion not the cauſe of death: but a teſtimony and witneſſe that they were ſtraungers from God. And wee know that men liue not any otherwiſe, than while they cleaue to their God, who alone is their life. Whereof it followeth that all the vngodlye, while they ſeeme in their owne conceits to be very liuely and freſh yet are they ſpiritually deade. By this meanes this place would agree with the ſeconde chapter to the Epheſians verſe <hi>11.</hi> where it is ſayd, You muſt remember that in time paſt when you were Gentils, and called vncircumciſion of that Circumciſion which is made with hande in the fleſh, at that time you were without Chriſt, ſeperated from the gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Iſraell, and ſtraungers from the promiſes. But Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phorically it ſhould be an alluſion to naturall vncircumciſion: but yet Paule ſhould ſpeake here of the ſtubbornneſſe of mans hart agaynſt God, and of nature diſtained with naughty affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions or motions. I rather hold the former expoſition, becauſe it agreeth better with the texte. For Paule maketh mention that vncircumciſion was no let but that they ſhould be partakers of the lyfe of Chriſt. Whereof it followeth, that Circumciſion de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogateth or taketh from the grace of God, that which alreadye they had obtayned. In that he aſcribeth death vnto vncircumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, he doth it not as vnto the cauſe, but as to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> badge or marke [thereof]. as he doth in that other place to the Epeſians, which I haue alleaged. And it is often vſed in the Scripture, by pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of the ſigne, to note the priuation of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thing, as Ge. <hi>3.22.</hi>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:7610:31"/> Leaſt happilye Adam eate of the fruite of life, and liue. For the tree did not giue life: but after it was taken awaye it was the ſign or badge of death. Paul in this place hath breefely ſet forth both, he ſayth they were dead through ſinnes. this is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cauſe: for ſinnes do ſeparate vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God. He putteth too, <hi>In the vncircum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion of the fleſh.</hi> This was the outwarde vncleanneſſe, a te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonie of ſpirituall death <hi>By forgiuing you,</hi> God in deede doth not quicken vs by onely forgiueneſſe of ſinnes: but in this place he doth peculiarly make mention thereof: becauſe free re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation with God, whiche ouerthroweth righteouſneſſe of workes, doth ſpecially belong to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preſent cauſe, wherein he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſeth about abrogating &amp; doing a way of ceremonies as more largely he hath treated in the Epiſtle to the Galathians. For the falſe Apoſtles in eſtabliſhing ceremonies, did binde the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences with a ſnare, from which Chriſt hath looſed them.</p>
               <p n="14">
                  <hi>14 Hauing put out the handwriting.</hi> Now doth he hande to hande cope with the falſe Apoſtles. For this was the ſtate of the caſe, Whether the keeping of ceremonies were neceſſarye vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the kingdome of Chriſt. But Paule contendeth, that cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies were aboliſhed, and that he may proue it, hee compareth them to a handwriting, whereby God holdeth vs as it were bounde, ſo that we cannot denye our guiltineſſe or debt. Nowe he ſayth we haue ſo bene deliuered from guiltineſſe, that the handwriting alſo hath bene put out, that it ſhoulde not be extant in memorie.<note place="margin">We vſe to ſub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ribe our name or marke with our hand wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy the bond or writing, and that here is ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>writing.</note> For we know that in all thinges while the hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>writing remaineth the bond or Obligation is of force: but after the handwriting is raſed, or torne in peeces, the debter is free and acquited. Whereof it followeth that all they doe diminiſhe the benefite of Chriſt, which as yet vrge ceremonies: as though we were not by him acquited and ſet free. for they reſtore to the handwriting the force which it had, that they maye ſtill keepe vs endaungered. This therefore is a true reaſon in diuinitie, to proue the aboliſhing of ceremonies: becauſe if Chriſt hath fully and perfectly redeemed vs from guiltineſſe and out of daunger, he ought alſo to take away the memoriall of the Obligation, whereby the conſciences may be at peace, and quiet in the ſight of God. for theſe two are annexed and tied together. Whereas
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:7610:31"/> the interpreters doe expounde this place diuerſly, there is none of them doth ſatiſfie me. Some doe thinke that Paule ſpeaketh ſimplye of the morall Lawe: but vntruely. for Paule is accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to call that portion (of the lawe) which is placed in ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, decrees: as in the Epiſtle to the Epheſians, and a little after. Speciallye the place to the Epheſians chap. <hi>2.</hi> ver. <hi>15.</hi> manifeſtlye proueth, that Paule in this place ſpeaketh of Ceremonies. And therefore better doe they whiche reſtrayne it to Ceremonyes: but in this poynte they alſo are deceyued, that they adde not a reaſon why it is called a hand-writing, or rather they alleage or aſſigne a cauſe that is contrary to the true cauſe indeede: neither yet doe they aptelye applye this ſimilitude to the Texte. But the (true) reaſon is, that all the ceremonies of Moſes hadde with them ſome confeſſion of guiltineſſe, which bounde the followers of them as it were with a more ſtraight bande before the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of GOD. As for example, What other thinges were the waſhinges, but a teſtimonie of filth and vncleanneſſe: As ofte as any ſacrifice was offred vp, did not the people that ſtoode by, beholde in the ſame an image or repreſentation of their own death? For when men didde place in their ſteede a harmeleſſe beaſt, they confeſſed that they themſelues deſerued that death. To be breeſe, looke how manye rites or ceremonies there were, ſo many ſhewes of mens guiltineſſe, and handwritinges of obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation were there. If any obiect and ſay, that they were ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes of the grace of God: as at this daye Baptiſme and the Euchariſt are vnto vs: the aunſwere is eaſie. for two thinges are to be conſidered in the old ceremonies: that whiche was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable vnto the tyme, and than that which lead men vnto the kingdome of Chriſt. Whatſoeuer was than done, did ſhewe forth nothing elſe but an obligation or binding. Grace was af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a ſorte ſuſpended and deferred, till the comming of Chriſt. not that the fathers were excluded from the ſame, but they had no preſent ſhewe thereof in their ceremonies. For they did ſee nothing beſide the blood of beaſts in ſacrifices: and in their waſhings they did ſee nothing but water. Therefore as concerning the preſent vewe or ſhewe, guiltineſſe remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: naye rather the ceremonies themſelues didde ſeale vp
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:7610:32"/> and ſigne guiltineſſe. After this maner alſo ſpeaketh the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle in all the Epiſtle to the Hebrues: becauſe he ſetteth Chriſte directly oppoſite and agaynſte the ceremonies. But howe is it now? The Sonne of God by his death hath not only deliuered vs from condemnation of death, but to the end our acquiting and diſcharge might be the more certayne, hee hath abrogated and done away thoſe ceremonies, that there ſhould appeare no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membraunce or monument of Obligation or building. This is ful and perfect libertie, that Chriſt by his blood hath wiped out not onely our ſinnes, but euery hand writing that might teſtifie that we were guiltie and endaungered vnto God. Eraſmus in his tranſlation hath diſordred and confounded the text ſet down by Paule, while he thus placeth it, Which was contrary to vs by decrees. Therefore holde faſt, as it is true and naturall, this reading which I haue ſet down. <hi>He hath taken out of the way, Hauing faſtned it to his Croſſe,</hi> He ſheweth the way whereby Chriſt hath raſed the handwriting. for as he faſtned to his croſſe our curſe and malediction, our ſinnes, and paynes alſo due to vs: ſo hath he done in like maner that bondage of the Law, &amp; what ſoeuer belongeth to the bynding of our conſciences. For being faſtned to the croſſe he toke all thinges vpon him: and therfore he bound them, that they might haue no more right and power ouer vs.</p>
               <p n="15">
                  <hi>15 Spoyling principallities.</hi> Without doubt he meaneth the Deuils, vnto whom the Scripture ſigneth theſe partes, in that they accuſe vs before the preſence of God. But Paule ſayth they are vnarmed, ſo that they can bring forth nothing againſte vs, the witneſſe and teſtee of our guiltineſſe being done away. And he addeth this by name, wherby he may declare that the victory which he hath gotten for himſelfe and vs ouer Sathan, is defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and blotted of the falſe apoſtles: and that we are bereft of the commoditie thereof, whenſoeuer they (goe about to) reſtore the old ceremonies. For if our libertie be the ſpoile, that Chriſt hath taken away from the Deuil, what doe other who wil bring vs backe into bondag, but reſtore vnto Sathan the ſpoiles, whereof he was cleane ſtripped? <hi>Triumphing ouer them in it.</hi> The greeke ſpeech will abide that we maye reade <hi>In himſelfe.</hi> naye rather the greater number of bookes haue <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> with
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:7610:32"/> an aſpiration: but the circumſtaunce of the place doth altogea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther require, that we reade it otherwiſe. for that which ſhoulde but coldly be ſpoken of Chriſt, is aptly and freelye referred to the croſſe. For as before he compared the croſſe to a noble Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nument of victorye, or to the pompe of a triumphe, in whiche Chriſt lead about his enemies: ſo alſo now doth he make it like to a triumphant chariot, in whiche hee hath bene ſeene ouer all the company. For although in the croſſe there was nothing but a curſe: yet it was ſo ſwallowed vp through the power of the ſonne of GOD, that after a ſorte it putte on a newe qualitie and nature. For no iudgement ſeate was ſo honourable, no princely throne ſo ſtately, no pompe of triumphe ſo notable, no chariot ſo loftie, as that gallowtree on which Chriſt hath ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued death, and the deuill the prince of death, and therefore hath vtterly trodden them vnder his feete.</p>
               <q>
                  <p n="16">16 Therefore let no man iudge you either in meate, or in drinke, or in a peece of a holydaye, or of the newmoone, or of the ſabbothes.</p>
                  <p n="17">17 Which are a ſhadow of thinges to come, but the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy is of Chriſt.</p>
                  <p n="18">18 Let no man take from you the victorie, meaning to doe it in lowlineſſe and in the ſeruice of Angels, thruſting himſelfe into thoſe thinges whiche hee hath not ſeene, in vayne being pufte vp by the mynde of his fleſh.</p>
                  <p n="19">19 And not holding the head, whereof the whole body being ſerued or ayded &amp; knit together by ioints and knittings, groweth with the encreaſe of god.</p>
               </q>
               <p n="16">
                  <hi>16 Therefore let no man.</hi> That which afore he ſpake of Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion, hee nowe extendeth to the difference of meates and dayes. For Circumciſion was the firſt order or degree towarde the obſeruing of the lawe: and then other thinges followed. <hi>To iudge,</hi> in this place ſignifieth to make one guilty of a fault, or to laye on religion, ſo that we may not any longer be free. He deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it than to be in the power of men, to make vs ſubiecte to the obſeruation of rites and ceremonies which Chriſte by his death
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:7610:33"/> hath taken away, and hath plucked our necks from the yoke of them, that we ſhould not ſuffer our ſelues to be enwrapped with the lawes which they make. And he doth couertly ſet Chriſt op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite and agaynſt all m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n, leſt any ſhould ſo boldly and raſhlye extoll himſelfe, that he would aſſaye to take awaye that whiche was giuen by him. <hi>In a peece of a holiday.</hi> Some take <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> for participation or partaking. Chryſoſtome ſuppoſeth that therefore he ſayde a Peece, becauſe they kept not all the feſtiual dayes or holydayes: neither yet did they exactly keepe holyday according to the preſcription &amp; appoyntment of the law: which (preſcription) was put out. Conſider whether it may not be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for <hi>ſegregating</hi> or <hi>parting.</hi> for they that make difference of dayes, doe as it were deuide one day from an other. Such parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion became the Iewes, that they ſhould keepe holye the dayes commaunded by parting them from other. Among Chriſtians ſuch deuidinges are ended. But ſome man will ſay, We doe as yet retayne ſome obſeruation of dayes. I aunſwere, Wee keepe not dayes, as though there were any religion in holydays, or as though it were not lawfull then to labour: but to haue regarde to policie or gouernment and order, and not to the dayes. And that is it which by and by he ioyneth.</p>
               <p n="17">
                  <hi>17 Which are a ſhadow of things to come.)</hi> Therefore doth he ſet at freedome Chriſtians from keeping them, becauſe they were ſhadowes at what time Chriſt as yet after a ſort was ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent. For he ſetteth ſhadowes oppoſite to reuealing or manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting: and abſence or beeing awaye to exhibiting or ſhewing forth. They than which as yet follow thoſe ſhadowes, doe euen like, as if one woulde conſider the ſhape or faſhion of a man by his ſhadowe, when as he hath the man himſelfe before him to looke vppon. For Chriſt is already made apparaunt vnto vs: and ſo wee haue the fruition of him as beeing preſent. <hi>The bodye,</hi> ſayth he, <hi>is of Chriſt,</hi> that is to ſay in Chriſt. For the ſubſtaunce of thoſe thinges, which the ceremonies in time paſt did figure, is ſette forth vnto vs before our eyes in Chriſte: for that he contayneth in himſelfe, whatſoeuer they ſigned or ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied to come to paſſe. Therefore eyther he ouerthroweth the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt ſhewing or manifeſtation of Chriſt, or elſe robbeth Chriſte of his power and vertue, &amp; as it were maketh him empty whiche
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:7610:33"/> calleth back ceremonies to be vſed agayne. Therefore if anye man in the world ſhall vſurpe vnto himſelfe the office of a iudge in this behalfe let vs not obay him: ſeing that Chriſt the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full iudge hath acquited vs and ſet vs free. For where he ſayth <hi>Let no man iudge you,</hi> hee ſpeaketh not to the falſe Apoſtles: but hee forbiddeth the Coloſſians that they put their neckes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der an vniuſt yoke. In deede of it ſelfe to abſtayne from ſwynes fleſhe, hurteth nothing at all: but the bynding to doe it is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious and hurtful, becauſe it maketh voyd the grace of Chriſt. If any man will demaunde, What ſhall we thinke then of oure Sacramentes? I aunſwere that they differ farre from the ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies. For as Paynters doe not paynte forth at the firſte draught the Image with liuely colours or picture like, but firſt doe drawe vnwroughte and diffuſde lynes out with a cole: ſo vnder the lawe the repreſentation or manifeſting of Chriſte, was vnpoliſhed and as it were of the firſt hand: but in our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentes he is behelde as ſet forth liuelye. Although Paule did fetche the matter further of: for he ſetteth oppoſite the bare ſight of the ſhadow agaynſt the firmeneſſe of the bodye: and admoniſheth that it is the token of a doting or franticke perſon, to take holde of vayne ſhadowes, when hee may with his hands handle the firme and ſolide bodye. Furthermore our Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes doe ſo figure Chriſt beeing abſente as touching ſighte and diſtaunce of place, that they teſtifie that he was once exhibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and ſhewed, and nowe alſo doe offer him to bee enioyed. They are not therefore bare ſhadowes: but rather badges and tokens of the preſence of Chriſt. for they contayne that Yea and Amen of all the promiſes of God, whiche is manifeſted in Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="18">
                  <hi>18 Leſt any take from you.)</hi> He alludeth to rumors of wreſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, vnto whome the victorye is on this condition appoynted, if they faynte not in the middeſt of their courſe, or after they haue begon to wreſtle. Hee putteth them in mynde than that the falſe Apoſtles goe aboute nothing elſe but to take from them the victorye: becauſe they leade them awaye from the rightneſſe of their courſe. whereof it followeth that they are to be ſhunned no otherwiſe than moſt contagious plagues.
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:7610:34"/> And the place is dilligently to be marked: that all they who leade vs away from the ſimplicitie of Chriſt, do craftily bereaue vs of the rewarde of ſupernall calling. <hi>Meaning in humilitie.</hi> Something muſt be vnderſtoode, and therefore in the Texte I haue put in To doe it. For he ſheweth a kynde of daunger, that they ought to take heede of, as if he ſhould ſaye, They mean to deceaue you of the victory, whatſoeuer they are that vnder the colour of humilitie and lowlineſſe, commende vnto you the ſeruice of Ang<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ls. For this they purpoſe, that you leauing the onely marke ſhould wander cleane out of the way. I reade <hi>low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe and the ſeruice of Angels,</hi> ioyning them together. for the later of theſe followeth the former. As at this daye the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtes, while they deuiſe like Philoſophers about worſhipping of Sayntes, doe pretende the ſame. For they gather their rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon from the debaſing or humbling of man, therefore wee muſt (ſaye they) ſeeke Mediatours, that may helpe vs. But therfore hath Chriſt humbled and debaſed himſelfe, that wee maye goe ſtraight vnto him, although we be miſerable and wretched ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. I knowe that <hi>ſeruice of Angels,</hi> is otherwiſe expounded of many: namely for ſuch ſeruice as is deliuered vnto men by Angels. for the Deuill vnder this tytle doth alwayes ſette out his iuggelinges and deceites. The Pope at this daye boaſteth all the trifles, wherewith he counterfeyteth the pure ſeruice of God, to be reuelations. Euen likewiſe in olde tyme didde the Cleargie auouche to bee by hande giuen them of the Aungels, whatſoeuer ſuperſtitions they like lying Marchantes tolde of or taught. And ſo they thinke that in this place are reprehended all fayned and forged ſeruices or worſhippinges, whiche are falſly commended and ſette forth vnder the Authoritie of Aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, but in my iudgement he doth rather reprehende the deuiſe or lye of ſeruing the Angels. For which reſpecte ſo diligentlye did he enforce himſelfe to this euen by and by after the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Epiſtle, that he brought the Angels vnder ſubiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that they might not darken the brightneſſe of Chriſt. To be ſhort as he in the firſt Chapter made his way to take away cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies: ſo did he in like maner to take away al impedime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts and lets which plucke vs awaye from Chriſt alone. among which
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:7610:34"/> which is the ſeruice of Angels. Superſtitions perſons haue fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the beginning worſhipped and ſerued Angels, that by their help they might haue acceſſe vnto God. The Platonicall Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers haue infected the Chriſtyan Church alſo with this error. For howſoeuer Auguſtine ſharpely inueieth agaynſte them in his tenth booke of the Citie of God, and doth greatly condemne whatſoeuer they reaſon and diſpute concearning the ſeruing of of Angels: Yet we ſee what hath come to paſſe. If any man conferre the writinges of Plato with the Popiſh diuinitie, hee ſhall finde that they haue drawne from Plato altogether thoſe thinges which they prattle concearning the ſeruice of Angels. This is the ſumme, Angels muſt be honoured, ſuche as Plato calleth Demones, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. that is, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of their happy or lucky interceſſion. This ſentence he put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth downe in Epinomide: and confirmeth it in Cratylus, and many other places. And what doe the Papiſtes differ at all from the ſame? But they denye not (ſay you) the Sonne of God to be a Mediator. No more doe they with whom Paule contendeth. but while they did fayne that by the helpe and ayde of Angels, they came to God, and that therefore ſome ſeruice muſt be done to them: in ſo doing they did place the Aungels in the ſeate of Chriſt, and decke and ſette them out with the office of Chriſte. Let vs than know that Paule in this place doeth condemne all forged and deuiſed ſeruice and worſhippinges, which are giuen eyther to the Angels or to the dead, as though after Chriſte, or with Chriſt, they ſhould be helping mediatours. For euen ſo much doe we depart and withdraw our ſelues from Chriſte, as we do ſet ouer the leſt portion of that which is proper and belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging to him to any other, whether the ſame be Aungels or elſe men. <hi>Thruſting in himſelfe into theſe thinges which he hath not ſeene.</hi> The Verbe <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the participle wherof Paule vſeth in this place, hath ſundrye ſignifications or meaninges. Whereas Eraſmus following Ierome hath tranſlated it, Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing loftily or proudly, it would not amis agree (with the text), if in any allowed authour there were an example of this ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. For we ſee dayly with how great boldneſſe, and with what a maieſtie and pride raſh headed perſons doe define or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine about thinges vnknowne. And ſurely in the preſente
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:7610:35"/> cauſe whiche Paule hath in hande, there is apparaunt a nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble doctrine. for when the Sorbonicall Diuines doe trifle a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the interceſſion or meditation of Saynts or Angels, they doe as it were oute of an Oracle pronounce that thoſe that are deade knowe and ſee our neceſſities, becauſe they ſee all things [as they ſaye] by meanes of a light that reſpecteth or ſhyneth back from God vpon them. And yet what is leſſe certayne? naye rather what is more obſcure doubtfull and intricate? But ſuch forſooth is their maſterlike licentiouſneſſe, that boldlye and without feare they auouche that which not onelye they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues knowe not, but that whiche cannot bee knowne of men. The meaning than would well agree, if that ſignification of the worde were any thing vſed: but ſimplye with the Greekes it is taken for <hi>Jncedere. i.</hi> to goe or to goe on it ſometyme ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth alſo to enquire or ſeeke after. If it like you ſo to take it in this place, Paule then reproueth fooliſh curioſitie, in ſearching after obſcure and darke matters, and ſuche thinges as are hidden and farre aboue our vnderſtanding. But in my conceyte I haue attayned the mynde and meaning of Paule, and haue truely and faythfully tranſlated it, after this maner, <hi>Thruſting himſelfe into thoſe thinges which he hath not ſeene.</hi> For the common ſignification of the Verbe <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> is, to enter ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnlye into an inheritaunce, or to vſurpe poſſeſſion, or to ſette in foote to a place. Therefore Budeus hath thus tranſlated this place, ſetting in foote, or entring on the poſſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of thoſe things which hee hath not ſeene: whoſe authoritie I haue followed, but I haue choſen out a more proper and fit worde. For in very deede ſuch fellowes breake through and thruſt themſelues into ſecretes and hidden thinges, whereof God as yet will haue no reuelation or knowledge to come vnto vs. A place to be marked to reproue the raſhneſſe of ſuch as enquire and ſearch after more than they ought. <hi>In vayne puf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed vp by the mind of the fleſh.</hi> He calleth the mynde of the fleſhe the thorow ſight of mans wit, how great ſoeuer it be. For he ſetteth it oppoſite vnto ſpirituall wiſedome which is reuealed vnto vs from heauen: according to that ſaying, Fleſhe and blood hath not reuealed that vnto thee: Math. chapt. <hi>16.</hi> ver. <hi>17.</hi> Whoſoeuer he is therefore that lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth to his owne reaſon, becauſe the force of carnall witte doth
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:7610:35"/> wholye, and throughly flouriſh in him, Paule ſheweth that hee is puffed vp in vayne. And ſurely it is but puffing and wynde, whatſoeuer wit it be that men haue of themſelues. nothing than is firme but in the worde of GOD, and by the illumination of the Spirite. And note, that they are called pufte vp, who thruſt in themſelues into fauour vnder the ſhewe of humilitie. For it falleth out (as Auguſtine doth elegantly write to Paulinus) by wonderous meanes in the ſoule of man, that it is more puffed vp and ſwelleth for falſe and diſſembled humilitie, than if open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly or manifeſtly it were proude.</p>
               <p n="19">
                  <hi>19 Not holding the head.)</hi> In one word he condemneth what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer is not referred to Chriſt. And hee confirmeth his opinyon for that all thinges flowe and depende thereof. Therefore if any call vs any whether elſe than vnto Chriſt, although otherwiſe he were great with heauen and earth, yet is he a vayn and light perſon: and therefore lette vs bee bolde to bidde him farewell. But marke of whome he ſpeaketh, namelye of thoſe who didde not openlye refuſe and denye Chriſt, but ſuche as not well vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding his office and power, ſoughte out other helpes of ſaluation and meanes, (as commonly they call them) and were not firmely rooted in him. <hi>Whereof the whole body.</hi> This hee ſimply meaneth, that the Church abideth and ſtandeth no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, than while all thinges are miniſtred vnto it by Chriſt the hedde: and therefore that all the ſafetie thereof is contayned in him. The body in deede hath his ſinewes, his beames, &amp; ioynts, or knittings: but yet al theſe haue no ſtrength or force but from the head, ſo that the whole knitting and binding of them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther commeth of it. What is than to bee done? [forſooth] the conſtitution or whole order of the body ſhall be right, if the head alone, which miniſtreth vnto all and ſingular members all that they haue, may without any lette haue the higheſt place. Paule nameth that the Encreaſe of God. whereby he declareth, that not euery increaſe is allowed of God, but that which is directed vnto the heade. For wee ſee that the kingdome of the Pope is not alone tall and bigge, but that it ſwelleth with a monſterous greatneſſe. But ſeeing it is not there to bee ſeene that Paule in this place requireth in the Church: what ſhall we ſay of it, but that it is a knobbye and crookebacked
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:7610:36"/> body, and a diſordred and il framed heape or pile, which will fall downe vpon it ſelfe?</p>
               <q>
                  <p n="20">20 If therefore ye be dead with Chriſte, from the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes of this Wolde: why are decrees preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed vnto you, as though ye liued in the world.</p>
                  <p n="21">21 Eate not, taſte not, handle not:</p>
                  <p n="22">22 Which all are into corruption by the abuſe it ſelfe, after the preceptes and doctrines of men.</p>
                  <p n="23">23 Which in deede haue a ſhewe of wiſedome in ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition, and in lowlineſſe of the minde, and in not regarding of the body: not in any honour to the fulfilling of the fleſh.</p>
               </q>
               <p n="20">
                  <hi>20 If ye be dead.</hi> He ſayed afore that the decrees or ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces were faſtned to the Croſſe of Chriſt: now he vſeth another figure or faſhion of ſpeaking, <hi>viz.</hi> that we are dead to them. as Galathins cap. <hi>2.19.</hi> he teacheth that we are dead to the Lawe and the law in like maner is dead to vs. The word Dead ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth abrogating or doing away: but when he ſayth Dead it is more liuely and effectually ſpoken. He ſayth than that the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſſians haue nothing to doe with decrees. Why ſo? for that they are dead with Chriſt vnto decrees, that is to ſay, after they are dead with Chriſt by regeneration, by his benefite they are deliuered from decrees: ſo that the ſame belong not any more at all vnto them. Hereof he concludeth, that they are not bounde by decrees, whiche the falſe Apoſtles aſſayed to laye vppon them.</p>
               <p n="21">
                  <hi>21 Eate not, taſte not.)</hi> Vntill this tyme they haue tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it, <hi>touche not.</hi> but whereas by and by followeth another word that ſignifieth the ſame thing: there is none but he ſeeth, how colde and ſtraunge a repetition it would be. Furthermore the verbe <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> among other thinges ſignifieth with the Greekes <hi>eſitare</hi> to pickle or eate, as I haue tranſlated it. Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarche in the life of Ceſar vſeth it, when he ſheweth that his ſouldyers in extreme ſcarcitie of all things, did eate ſuch things as were not before meete to be eaten. And this order once is na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall, and alſo very fit for the circumſtaunce of the place. For
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:7610:36"/> Paule doth in vſing and immitating their own wordes, paynte forth, how farre their waywardneſſe is accuſtomed to proceede, who by their lawes do intangle the conſciences. Euen from the beginning they are more rough than needes. Therefore they begin with forbidding not onely to eate, but alſo to eate lightly or a little. After they haue got that which they woulde, than goe they beyonde that commaundemente: ſo that afterwarde they pronounce it to bee a great euill to taſte that whiche they will not haue eaten. At leaſt for a manne but to touche it, they make it a Purgatorie matter, to deſerue the paynes of Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie. To bee briefe, there is no ende when menne haue taken vpon them like tyrants ouer other mens ſoules, but there are euery day newe lawes put to the olde, and many times there ſtart vp newe decrees. What a playne and euident view may a man haue hereof in the Papacie. Therfore excellently well doth Paule who warneth that mens traditions are a Labyrinth or maſe, whereby the conſciences are more and more enwrapped: nay rather ſnares, which doe ſo bind in the beginning, that in proceſſe of time they will at length ſtrangle.</p>
               <p n="22">
                  <hi>22 Which all are into corruption.</hi> With a double argument he confuteth the decrees wherof he ſpake: firſt for that they put religion in outwarde and frayle thinges which belong nothing to the ſpirituall kingdome of God: ſecondly becauſe they are of men, and not of God. He contendeth with the firſt argumente alſo. Ro. <hi>14.17.</hi> The kingdome of God is not in meate &amp; drinke. Alſo <hi>1</hi> Cor. <hi>6.13.</hi> Meate for the belly, and the belly for meates, God will deſtroy both of them. And Chriſt in himſelfe [ſayth], Whatſoeuer entreth into the mouth, defileth not a man. Math. <hi>15.11.</hi> becauſe it goeth downe into the belly, and is caſt forth. The ſumme is, that the ſeruice of GOD, true godlyneſſe and the holyneſſe of Chriſtians conſiſteth not in meate, &amp; drink, and apparaile: which are things that paſſe awaye, are vnder corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and periſh by abuſe. For abuſe is properly ſaide [or meant] of ſuch things as vſe corrupteth or mareth. Therefore naught worth are precepts or decrees touching thoſe things which are ſette out to laye religion vppon the conſciences. But in the Papacie you ſhall ſcarce finde anye other holyneſſe ſauing in trifling obſeruations of corrutible things. The other confuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:7610:37"/> followeth, namely that they came from men, and haue not God their authour or beginner. with which flaſh of lightning he hurleth down and conſumeth all the traditions of men. And why? This is Paules maner of reaſoning, They doe iniurie to Chriſt, and make voyde his death, that bring agayne the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences into bondage. For whatſoeuer is of mans inuenting, byn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth not the conſcience.</p>
               <p n="23">
                  <hi>23 Which in deede haue a ſhew.)</hi> It it a preuention, in which while he doth yeelde to his aduerſaries that which they mighte alleage, he doth withall account it euery whit as nothing. For it is aſmuch as if he ſhould ſay, that he wayeth it not that they haue a ſhew of wiſedome. But ſhew is oppoſite or contrarye to truth. for it is an appearaunce, (as commonlye they ſpeake it) while beguileth becauſe of likelyhoode. And marke of what co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loures this ſhewe conſiſteth after the mynde of Paule. He na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth three, a choyſe in ſeruing or worſhipping, lowlineſſe or humilitie, and a neglecting of the body. Superſtition with the Greekes is calle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: which word Paule vſeth here in this place. But he had reſpect to the etemologie and naturall ſignification of the word. For <hi>Ethelothreſcia</hi> word for word is <hi>voluntarius cultus,</hi> a voluntarie ſeruice, which menne of their owne choyſe or determining doe appoynt &amp; chooſe to themſelues without the commaundement of GOD. Mens traditions doe therefore like vs, becauſe they are agreeable to diſpoſition: for euery man in his owne brayne will deuiſe and inuente formes and figures of them. this is the firſt colour. The ſeconde is low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, becauſe obedience both to God and man is pretended: ſo that menne maye not refuſe, no not vniuſt and wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full burthen. And for the moſt part this is in theſe maner of tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſeeme to be maruaylous good excerciſes of low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe. They are wel liked alſo in the third colour, becauſe they ſeeme to auayle very much toward the mortifiing of the fleſhe, while there is no regarde had of the body. But Paule biddeth farewell to theſe ſhewes and coloures. for euen that whiche is high before men, is often times abhomination before God more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is a diſobedient obedience, and a peruerſe and ſacrile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious lowlineſſe or humilitie, which paſſeth ouer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> authority of
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:7610:37"/> God vnto men. and the neglecting of the bodye is not ſo muche worth that that it ought to be ſet out as a ſeruice of God. But ſome man wil maruel why Paule toke no more paynes in pluc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king off theſe viſars. I aunſwere, Firſte that he contented him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe with the onelye worde Shewe, and it was inoughe. For thoſe principles whiche hee had taken from the contrary parte, are inuiſible, [namelye] that the bodye is in Chriſt. and that therefore they did nothing elſe but mocke ſillye poore men, in that they did ſet before them ſhadowes. Moreouer that the ſpirituall Kingdome of Chriſte is not occupyed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boute frayle and corruptible elementes. Thirdlye that by the death of Chriſt ſuche obſeruations are deade, that they ſhoulde not a whit belong to vs. Fourthlye, that GOD is our onely Lawgiuer. Whatſoeuer maye bee broughte on the contrarye ſide, although it haue ſome fayre ſhewe or bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, yet is it a vaniſhing and frayle ſhewe. Secondlye he accounted it inough to moniſhe the Coloſſians that they were not deceaued with the ſhewe of vaine and emptye thinges: and it was not nedefull to ſtande longer about the diſprouing of them. It ought to bee as commonly knowne as is a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbe, among all godly perſons, that the ſeruice of GOD muſt not bee meaſured after our thoughte and meaning: nor yet that any ſeruice is legitimate or lawfull, for that it liketh vs. This alſo ought to be as well knowne, that this is the humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and lowlineſſe we owe to God, that wee ſimplie obeye that which he biddeth, that we leane not to our owne wiſedome. &amp;c. And that this is the boundes of lowlineſſe towarde men, that by charitie euery one ſubmitte himſelfe vnto others. And whereas they contend that the wantonneſſe of the fleſhe is kept downe by abſtinence of meates, the aunſwere is eaſye: wee maye not therefore abſtaine from any certayne kinde of meate, as being vnclean, but we muſt ſparingly eat thoſe things which we feede of: as well that we may ſoberly and meaſurably beſtow &amp; order the guifts of God, as alſo that we lie not entangled in much ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and drinking; and forget thoſe thinges that belong vnto God. Wherefore it was inough for him to ſay theſe were viſars and ſhewes: that the Coloſſians being warned might arme the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues againſt a falſe and coloured pretence. So at this daye
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:7610:38"/> the Papiſtes lack no faire ſhewes, wherewith they maye com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mende and ſet out their lawes, though partly they be vngodlye and tyrannicall, partly vayne and trifling. But whan we haue yielded all vnto them: yet this confutation of Paule muſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide, which is ynough and ynough alone to diſcuſſe all their va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, and yet I will not ſpeake howe farre differente they are from that ſo honeſt a ſhew, which Paule deſcribeth. The princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall holyneſſe of the Papacie at this day is in Monkerie, but what that is, I am aſhamed and agrieued to ſpeake of, leaſte I ſhoulde ſtirre ſo foule a ſtinke. Furthermore it is worth while here to conſider, how readily, nay rather how haſtily and head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dilye mans nature and diſpoſition is caried into fayned and deuiſed worſhippinges and ſeruice. For in this place the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle liuely and ſkilfullye paynteth out the ſtate of olde Monke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie: whiche within an hundred yeares after his death didde ſo muche preuayle as though hee hadde neuer made worde of it. Therfore the heate of men was wonderous madde to ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which could not be brideled with ſo plain a leſſon of God, but that it would breake out, as the hiſtories doe teſtifie. <hi>Not in any honour.</hi> Honour ſignifieth regarde or care, after the vſe of the hebrew tongue. Honour widdowes: that is to ſay haue regard of them. And Paule doth diſlike that, that they teach to caſte a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the care for the bodie. For as God forbiddeth that we ſhold out of meaſure cheriſh the bodie: ſo he commaundeth to geue it as much as is neceſſarie. Therefore Paule Rom. <hi>13.14.</hi> doeth not ſimply condemne care for the fleſhe, but ſuche a care as ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth for the luſtes. Haue no regarde of the fleſhe, ſayth hee, vnto luſtes. What than doeth Paule note to bee amiſſe in thoſe traditions whereof he ſpeaketh? for that they giue no honour vnto the bodie for enlarging the fleſhe: that is to ſay ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the meaſure of neceſſitie. For <hi>fullfilling</hi> in this place, ſignifieth a mediocritie or meane vſage, which reſtraineth it ſelf to the bare vſe of nature, and ſo it is vſed as the contrary to plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and all ſuperfluous dellicacie. for nature is content with a few things. Therefore to denye that which nature requireth to ſuſtayne the neceſſitie of life, is no leſſe contrary to pietie, than voyde of humanitie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:7610:38"/>
               <head>¶ The thirde Chapter.</head>
               <q>
                  <p n="1">1 Therefore if you haue riſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with Chriſt, ſeeke thoſe things that are aboue, where Chriſt is ſitting on the righte hand of God.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Thinke vpon thoſe thinges that are aboue, &amp; not which are vpon the earth.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 For you be dead, and your life is hidden with Chriſt in God.</p>
                  <p n="4">4 But when Chriſt your life ſhall appeare, then alſo ſhall ye appeare with him in glory.</p>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>HE ſetteth against thoſe vayne</hi> excerciſes which the falſe Apoſtles did vrge, as though perfection were placed in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, true excerciſe wherewith it becommeth true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians to be occupied: whiche doth not a little make for the cauſe. For while wee perceaue what God woulde haue vs doe, wee doe eaſilye afterward ſette nought by the inuentions of men. Whileſt it appeareth that that which God ſetteth out for vs is farre more high and noble, than that which men beate into our heades, wee leaue men, and our mindes grow more and more readie and willing to follow God. Paule in this place exhorteth the Coloſſians to the conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and practiſe of a heauenlye life. But what doe his aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries? they would detayne them in childiſh rudimentes. This doctrine then cauſeth ceremonies to bee more little ſette by. Whereof it appeareth that Paule doth ſo exhort in this place, that he confirmeth his former doctrine. For in deſcribing firme or ſounde Godlineſſe and holineſſe of life, hee directeth his talke to this poynt, that thoſe vayne ſhewes of mens traditions maye waſt and weare away. He doth withall preuente an Obiection wherewith the falſe Apoſtles might burthen him, What then? haddeſt thou rather that men ſhould be idle then to giue them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:7610:39"/> to theſe excerciſes, what kind of ones ſoeuer they be? Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as therfore he biddeth Chriſtians to applye themſelues to farre more excellent ſtudies, he cutteth of occaſion from this malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſurmiſe, nay rather he chargeth them with no ſmal ſpite, for that with things of nought they call away, and hinder the right courſe of the godly.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <hi>1 If ye are riſen.</hi> Aſcending followeth riſing agayne, if then we be the members of Chriſt, we muſt aſcende into heauen: becauſe that he being rayſed from the dead, is taken vp into heauen, that he might draw vs with him. And we ſeeke thoſe thinges which are aboue, while in our mindes we are truely pilgrimes in this worlde, and are not tied to the ſame. The worde, <hi>thinke on,</hi> doth more expreſſe a paynefulneſſe in taking care, and a vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mencie: as if he ſhoulde ſaye, Meditate this wholy: apply your witte to this, applye your minde to this. But if wee oughte to thinke on nothing but that which is heauenly: for that Chriſt is in heauen: how much leſſe ſhall it be meete to ſeeke Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe on the earth? Lette vs remember than that this is a true thinking on Chriſte, and an holye, whiche forthwith rauiſheth vs vp into heauen, that we maye worſhippe him there, and that our minds may dwell with him. As touching that which belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth to the right hand of God, it is not ſhut vp in heauen: but it filleth the whole world. Furthermore Paule made me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tion ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of in this place, that he might ſhew that Chriſt embraceth vs by his power: leſt wee ſhoulde thinke the diſtaunce of place to bee a cauſe of ſeparation or diuorce betweene vs and him: and that withall, his maieſtie might wholy rauiſh vs into the reueren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing therof.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2 Not which are vpon earth.</hi> Hee doth not vnderſtande, as afterward he doth, vicious deſires whiche raigne in earthlye men: neyther yet riches, or Fieldes, or houſes, or whatſoeuer things elſe belonging to this preſent life, which we muſt vſe as though we vſed them not: but he followeth as yet his diſputatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> concerning ceremonies which he maketh like vnto trifling lets, which conſtrain vs to creepe on the ground. Chriſt, ſayth he, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth vs vp vnto him: but thoſe leade you downeward. For it is a concluſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; an expoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of thoſe maters which lately he touched
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:7610:39"/> concerning the dying of ceremonies by the death of Chriſt. as if he ſhould ſay, Therfore are ceremonies dead to you by the death of Chriſt, and you vnto them, that beinge lifted vp into heauen with Chriſt, ye ſhould thinke onelye vpon heauenlye thinges. Therefore let goe earthlye thinges. I will not contend a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt other who think otherwiſe: but certaynelye mee thinkes the Apoſtle doeth ſo proceede ſteppe by ſteppe orderly, that firſt and formoſt he ſetteth oppoſite traditions touching trifling mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, vnto the meditation of an heauenly life: and after that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth further, as we ſhall ſee.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3 For ye be dead.)</hi> He cannot riſe agayne with Chriſte, who firſt hath not died with him. Therefore hee bringeth his argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, from riſing agayne to dying, as from the conſequente to the accedent, ſignifiing that wee muſt bee deade to the Worlde, that we maye liue to Chriſte. Why hath hee taughte that wee muſt ſeeke the thinges that are aboue? becauſe the life and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation of the godly is aboue. Why doth he teache that thoſe thinges are now to be let paſſe, which are vpon the earth? be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are dead to the world. as if he ſhoulde ſaye, Death goeth before that riſing againe which I haue ſpoken of. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore both of theſe muſt be ſeene in you. This is worth the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, that our life is hidden: leaſt wee repyne or complayne, if oure life beeing vnder the ignominie of the Croſſe, and buried vnder manifolde ſorrowes, differ nothing from death: but that we muſt paciently expect and waight for the day of reuelatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or appearaunce. And that our waiting be not painful and greuous, let vs note the parcels, <hi>In God,</hi> and <hi>with Chriſt:</hi> which declare, that our life is out of daunger, although it appeare not. For euen God is faythefull and truſtye, and therefore hee will not denye that whiche was layde vp with him,<note place="margin">The La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine is <hi>do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitum,</hi> which alſo ſignifyeth a guage or pledge.</note> nor deceaue in that hee tooke to keepe: and the ſocietie and felloweſhippe of Chriſte bringeth yet more ſecurytie and aſſuraunce. For what is more to bee deſyred, than for our lyfe to remayne with the verye wellſpring of lyfe? Wherefore there is no couſe whye wee ſhoulde bee terryfied, if while wee looke aboute on euery ſide, we ſee lyfe on no ſide. For by hope we are ſafe. But thoſe things which are now ſene to the eyes, are not
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:7610:40"/> hoped for. Neither yet doth he teach that our life is hidden after the opinyon of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world only, but alſo according to our own mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning or vnderſtanding: becauſe this is a true and neceſſary ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periment and triall of our hope, whiles we as compaſſed aboute with death, doe ſeeke life elſe where than in the worlde.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <hi>4 But when Chriſt ſhall appeare.)</hi> A pleaſaunte and godlye comforte, that the comming of Chriſt ſhalbe the manifeſtation and appearaunce of our life. And withall he admoniſheth howe prepoſterous the deſire of the life to come is, if a man refuſe to ſuffer patiently euen vntill that daye. For if our life be ſhut vp in Chriſte, vntill hee ſhall appeare, it muſte needes bee hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den.</p>
               <q>
                  <p n="5">5 Mortifie therefore your members which are vppon the earth, fornication, vncleanneſſe, inordinate affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, euill concupiſcence and couetouſneſſe, whiche is I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatrie.</p>
                  <p n="6">6 For which the wrath of God commeth vpon the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of diſobedience.</p>
                  <p n="7">7 In which you alſo walked in time paſt, when you liued in them.</p>
                  <p n="8">8 But now put you away alſo al wrath, fuming, maliciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, curſed ſpeaking, filthie communication oute of your mouth.</p>
               </q>
               <p n="5">
                  <hi>5 Mortifie therefore.)</hi> Hitherto he hath ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the contempt of the world: now he goeth farther, and intreateth to an higher (kinde of) Philoſophie, concearning the mortification of the fleſhe. That this may be done the more playnly, let vs note that mortification is twofolde or double. the firſt reſpecteth thoſe thinges that are about vs, of which he hath entreated hetherto. the other is inward: namelye of the diſpoſition and will, and of our whole nature corrupted and infected. And he reckeneth vp certayne vices, which he vnproperly calleth members, but yet elegantly. For he imagineth our nature (to be) as a maſſe or ſowe caſt out of many vices. They are then our members, which ſticke vnto vs as cloſe as it were, as burres. He alſo calleth them <hi>earthly,</hi> alluding to that which he ſpake, in the ſecond verſe, <hi>viZ.
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:7610:40"/> 
                     <hi>Not which are vpon the earth,</hi>
                  </hi> but yet in another ſence. This kinde of ſpeaking is as much as if he had ſayde, I haue warned you that earthly thinges are not to be regarded: yet muſt you trauayle about this that you mortifie the vices whiche detayne you in the earth. And he meaneth that we as long as the vices of the fleſhe doe floriſhe in vs, are earthly: but we are made hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenlye by the renuing of the Spirite. After <hi>whoredome</hi> hee putteth <hi>Vncleanneſſe,</hi> by which worde he putteth all kinde of wantonneſſe, wherewith lecherous men defile themſelues. Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to theſe is added <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> that is in latine <hi>Mollities,</hi> whiche is engliſhed <hi>inordinate affection,</hi> which comprehendeth all the allurementes of Lecherie. Although this word doeth otherwiſe ſignifie perturbations or trouble of the mynde, and vntempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate motions contrarie to reaſon: yet to this place doth well a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree <hi>mollities.</hi> Why couetouſneſſe is called the worſhipping of Images, ſeeke out of the Epiſtle to the Epheſians, leſt I ſhould doe one thing twice.</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <hi>6 For which commeth.</hi> I reproue not Eraſmus for tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it, <hi>is wont to come.</hi> Yet becauſe the preſent tence is in the Scripture often taken in place of the future tence, according to the manner of the Hebrew tongue: I choſe rather to leaue you the reading that was the meane, whiche might bee fitted to ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſence. Therefore he warneth the Colloſſians eyther of the vſitate iudgementes of God, which are dayly ſeene: or elſe of the vengeaunce which once he hath denounced to the vngodlye, and which hangeth ouer their heades: and yet ſhall not bee ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted before the laſt day. Although I willingly allow that for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mer ſence and expoſition, that God who is the perpetuall iudge of the world, is accuſtomed to puniſh the wickedneſſe wherof he ſpeaketh. And by name he ſayth the wrath of God ſhall come, or is wont to come, vpon vnbeleeuers &amp; diſobedient perſons, rather then threatneth to them ſuch a matter. For God had rather wee ſhoulde ſee his wrath in the reprobate, that feele it in our ſelues. When the promiſes of grace are openly pronounced, euerye one of the godlye ought no otherwiſe to embrace them, than as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perlye appoynted for themſelues. And ſo lette vs feare the threatninges of wrath and deſtruction, that that which is allot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:7610:41"/> which is alotted to the reprobate, may bee vnto vs a document or leſſon. In deede God is often ſayde to be alſo angry with his Children: and ſometime hee doth ſharpely chaſten their ſinnes. But in this place Paule is in hande about eternall deſtruction, the viewe or Spectacle whereof appeareth in the onelye repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates. In ſumme, as often as GOD threatneth hee doeth as it were trauerſlye ſet out vnto vs the payne, that wee behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the ſame in the reprobate, maye be feared awaye from ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</p>
               <p n="7">
                  <hi>7 In which ye did walke.)</hi> Eraſmus did ill for that hee refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red it to men, tranſlating it thus, <hi>amongeſt whome.</hi> for Paule without doubt meant it of vices: in which he ſayth the Coloſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans were conuerſant, at what time they liued in them. For Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing and Walking differ one from another, as abilitie to doe, and doing: Liuing goeth afore, and Walking followeth. Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lathians the <hi>5.</hi> chapter and <hi>25.</hi> verſe, If you liue in the ſpirite, walke alſo in the Spirite. By theſe wordes he declareth that it is an heynous thing, if they being any longer addicted to vices, to which they are dead by Chriſt, are giuen ouer vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Loke the <hi>6.</hi> chapter to the Romaynes. It is an argument taken from the priuation or taking away y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cauſe, to the priuation or taking awaye the effect.</p>
               <p n="8">
                  <hi>8 But now. &amp;c.</hi> That is ſeeing you haue ceaſed to liue in the fleſhe. For this is the force and nature of mortification, that all corrupt affections are quenched in vs, ſo that hereafter ſinne engendereth not in vs his accuſtomed fruites. Whereas I haue tranſlated it <hi>fuming,</hi> in greeke it is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which word ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a more haſtie or heady kinde of heate, than is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. And here he reckoneth vp kindes of vices that are contrary to the former, as you may readily ſee.</p>
               <q>
                  <p n="9">9 Lye not one to another, ſeing you haue put off the olde man with his deedes.</p>
                  <p n="10">10 And you haue put on the new man whiche is renewed into knowledge, after the image of him which crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him.</p>
                  <p n="11">
                     <pb n="67" facs="tcp:7610:41"/>11 Where there is no Greeke nor Iewe, Circumciſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on nor vncircumciſion: Barbarian, Scythian, bondman nor freeman: but Chriſt all thinges, and in all thinges.</p>
                  <p n="12">12 Put on therefore as the elect of God, holy and beloued the bowels of compaſſion, courteſie, humility, kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, long ſuffering.</p>
                  <p n="13">13 Forbearing one another, and forgiuing if any haue a controuerſie againſt another, as Chriſt hath forgiue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you, ſo [doe] you alſo.</p>
               </q>
               <p n="9">
                  <hi>9 Lye not.</hi> When he forbiddeth lying, he condemneth all ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of ſubteltie, and all euill practiſes of deceite and falſhoode. for I doe not take it as meant of ſlaunders onely, but generally I make it contrarye to ſinceritie and true dealing. therefore I might more briefely thus tranſlate it, and I cannot ſaye whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther alſo better, Lye not one to another. And hee proſecuteth that his argument of the ſocietie or fellowſhippe whiche the faythfull haue with the death and reſurrection of Chriſte: but he vſeth other manners of ſpeaking. The Olde man ſignifieth that whatſoeuer it is that wee bring out of our mothers wombe, and whatſoeuer we are by nature. Such put off him as are renewed by Chriſt. contrariwiſe the new man is hee whiche is reformed and faſhioned agayne by the Spirite of Chriſte in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the obedience of righteouſneſſe: or elſe it is nature reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red into true ſoundneſſe and integritie by the ſame Spirite. And the olde man in order goeth before the newe, becauſe wee are firſte borne of Adam, after that wee are borne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne by Chriſte. And as that which wee haue of Adam, waxeth olde, and enclyneth to ruine and decay: ſo that whiche we obtayne by Chriſt, remaineth perpetually, is not frayle or mortall, but rather is caried vnto immortalitie. This place is to be marked, becauſe out of it may be gathered a definition of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation or newe byrth. For it comprehendtth two partes, the putting off of the olde man, and the buildinge vppe of the newe of both which partes Paule here maketh mention.
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:7610:42"/> And it muſt be marked, that the old man is diſcerned and iudged by his workes, as the tree by the fruites. whereof it follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth, that vnder the name of the olde man is meant the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe that is bredde in vs.</p>
               <p n="10">
                  <hi>10 Which is renued into knowledge.</hi> Firſte hee ſheweth that newneſſe of life conſiſteth in knowledge: not for that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and ſimple knowledge is ſufficient, but hee ſpeaketh of the illuminating of the holye Ghoſt, which is liuely and effectuous, ſo that not only it doth lighten beeing kindled with the light of truth, but doth tranſforme and newlye faſhion the whole man. And this is that whiche ſtraightwaye hee addeth, that wee are renued after the Image of GOD. And the Image of GOD hath reſidence in the whole ſoule, when not reaſon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, but alſo the will is righte. Hereof alſo wee learne, as well what is the ende and finall cauſe of our regeneration, that is to ſaye that we maye bee made like vnto God, and that his glorye may ſhine out in vs: as alſo what the image of God is, whereof mention is made in Moſes Gen. <hi>9.6.</hi> namely the right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and integritie of the whole ſoule, ſo that man doeth repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent the wiſedome, righteouſneſſe &amp; goodneſſe of God as it were a loking glaſſe. Hee doth ſpeake ſomewhat otherwiſe to the Epheſians, but in the ſame ſence: ſee the place cap <hi>4.24.</hi> And withall Paule moniſheth, that there is nothing more excellent whereunto the Coloſſians may aſpire, becauſe this muſt bee our higheſt perfection and bleſſedneſſe, <hi>(viZ)</hi> to beare the Image of God.</p>
               <p n="11">
                  <hi>11 Where there is no Iewe.</hi> This hee added of ſette pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, that hee mighte agayne drawe awaye the Colloſſians from Ceremonies. For thus ſounde the wordes, Chriſtian per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection needeth not a whit theſe outward obſeruations. naye ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they are things vtterly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to it. For vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of <hi>Vncircumciſion</hi> and <hi>Circunciſion,</hi> of <hi>Iewe</hi> and <hi>Greeke,</hi> hee comprehendeth all outwarde thinges by the figure <hi>Synecdoche.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Synecdoche,</hi> is whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> part of a thing is vſed for the whole thing</note> Theſe wordes whiche followe, namelye, Barbarian, Scy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thian, Bondman, Freeman, are added to amplifie the matter. <hi>Chriſte all thinges, and in all thinges,</hi> That is to ſaye, Chriſt alone holdeth boeth foreſhippe and poupe, (as they
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:7610:42"/> ſaye) beginning and ende. Furthermore by Chriſt he vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the ſpirituall righteouſneſſe of Chriſt, which aboliſheth ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies, as afore is ſeene. They are therefore in true perfec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſuperfluous: inſomuch that they oughte to haue no place, for elſe Chriſte were offred iniurie, as though it were neede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to call foorth theſe helpes to ſupplye his defecte and want.</p>
               <p n="12">
                  <hi>12 Put on therefore.</hi> As he hath reckoned vp ſome partes of the olde man, ſo now alſo doth he recken vp ſome partes of the newe. Than, ſaytth he, ſhall it appeare that yee are renewed by Chriſt, if you ſhall bee mercifull and gentle. &amp;c. For theſe are the effectes and teſtimonies of renouation or beeing a newe man. The exhortation than dependeth of the ſeconde member: and therefore he retayneth a metaphor in the worde <hi>put ye on.</hi> In the firſt place he putteth <hi>bowels of mercy,</hi> by which kinde of ſpeach, he noteth an earneſt and entire affection of mercye. Secondlye he putteth <hi>Courteſie</hi> (For ſo it liketh me to tranſlate <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> (wherewith wee are made amya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and beloued. Next to this he ioyneth Humilitie: becauſe no man will be curteous and tractable, but he who hauing put a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye pride and hautineſſe of mynde, hath ſubmitted himſelf vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to modeſtie, challenging nothing to himſelfe. <hi>Kindneſſe</hi> which followeth, extendeth largelier than <hi>Courteſie.</hi> for courteſie is principally in the countenaunce and ſpeeche: and kindneſſe is alſo in the inwarde affection. But in as much as it falleth out oftentimes that we happen vpon wicked perſons and vnthanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full: pacience is needefull, which may nouriſh in vs gentleneſſe or kindneſſe. At length he expoundeth what hee hath meant by <hi>long ſuffering:</hi> namely that with mercy we imbrace one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and forgiue alſo when ought ſhalbe done amiſſe. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is an harde and difficulte matter, hee confirmeth his doctrine by example of Chriſt, and teacheth that the like is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired at our hands: that we, as being ſo ofte and ſo exceeding faultie are notwithſtanding receaued of Chriſte into fauour, ſhould ſhewe the like kindneſſe to our neighboures, forgiuing them whatſoeuer they haue committed agaynſt vs. Therefore he ſayth, <hi>If any haue a controuerſie againſt another.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he meaneth, that not euen iuſt reuenge according to mans o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:7610:43"/> is to be perſued <hi>As the elect of God.</hi> In this place I take <hi>elect</hi> for them that are ſegregate or ſet apart. as if he ſhold ſay, God hath choſen you vnto himſelfe on that condition, &amp; ſanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified you, and taken you into his fauour, that you ſhoulde bee mercifull. &amp;c. He that hath not theſe vertues, doth in vayn boaſt himſelfe holy and beloued of God: in vayne doth he recken him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe among the number of the faithfull.</p>
               <q>
                  <p n="14">14 For all thoſe thinges ſake, put on charitie, which is the bond of perfection.</p>
                  <p n="15">15 And the peace of God obtain the victory in your harts to the which you are called alſo in one body, and be you thankefull.</p>
                  <p n="16">16 Let the word of Chriſt dwell with you aboundantly in all wiſedome, in teaching and warning your ſelues in Pſalmes, Hymnes, and ſpiritual Songs with grace, ſinging in your harts to the Lord.</p>
                  <p n="17">17 And whatſoeuer you ſhall doe in worde or deede, do it all in the name of the Lord Ieſus, giuing thankes to God and the Father by him.</p>
               </q>
               <p n="14">
                  <hi>14 For all thoſe things.</hi> Whereas ſome haue tranſlated it, <hi>Beſide all thoſe things,</hi> in my iudgment it is coldlye done. It would better accord to doe it thus, <hi>Before all theſe things.</hi> But I haue rather choſen the vſed ſignification of the word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. For ſeeing that all thoſe thinges which he hath reckoned vp hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, doe ſpring out of charitie: hee doeth rightlye nowe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horte the Coloſſians, that they mayntayne Charitie among themſelues, for thoſe thinges ſake: that is to ſaye that they maye bee mercifull, kynde, and eaſie to forgiue. as if hee ſhoulde ſaye, that then they ſhoulde bee ſuche if they haue cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie. For where as charitie is miſſing, in vayne are all thoſe thinges required. And to the ende hee maye the more ſette it out, hee calleth it, The bonde of perfection: whereby hee ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth that the whole company of all vertues are comprehended vnder it. For this is the very rule of the whole life and of the whole deedes, after whiche whatſoeuer is not ruled out, it is
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:7610:43"/> faultie and naught, whatſoeuer fayre ſhewe otherwiſe it hath. That is the cauſe why in this place it is called the bande of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, becauſe nothing in our life is well framed that is not directed vnto it: but whatſoeuer wee take in hand it is a meere ſcattering. But the Papiſtes are to bee laughed at, who a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe this teſtimonie to builde vp iuſtification by workes. Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, ſaye they, is the bond of perfection, but perfection is righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe; therefore by charitie we are iuſtified. It is aunſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red two wayes. for Paule reaſoneth not here how men are made perfecte before GOD: but how they maye liue perfectlye a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong themſelues. For this is the naturall and true expoſition of the place, <hi>viz.</hi> that the other thinges ſhall fall oute well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning our life, if charitie floriſh and growe amongeſt vs. But if it be graunted that charitie is righteouſneſſe, in vayne and childiſhlye doe they out of that contende, that wee are iuſtified by charitie for where ſhall perfect charitie be founde? And we doe not therefore ſay that men are iuſtified by fayth onlye, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe to obſerue the Lawe is not righteouſneſſe: but rather, that whereas we are all tranſgreſſors of the Law and without righteouſneſſe of our owne, we are are compelled to borrowe righteouſneſſe of Chriſte. Therefore the onelye righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe by fayth remayneth, becauſe charitie is in no wiſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect.</p>
               <p n="15">
                  <hi>15 And the peace of God.)</hi> Hee nameth that peace whiche God hath ordayned and eſtabliſhed among vs, as ſhall appeare by that which followeth, and that will he haue to raigne in our hartes. But he vſeth a Metaphor that is very fit. for as among wreſtlers, he that hath ouercome all others, carieth awaye the palme or victorye: ſo will he haue the peace of God to be ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour ouer the affections of the fleſh, which cary vs away often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to contentions, diſagreements, braules, and priuie grud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. He forbiddeth then to giue the bridle to ſuche naughtie af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections. But becauſe it is a harde matter to holde them backe, hee alſo ſheweth a remedye: [that is] that the victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye maye bee in the handes of the peace of GOD: becauſe it muſt bee a bridle, wherewith all the affections of the fleſhe maye be helde backe. Therefore he ſayth in <hi>your hartes,</hi> becauſe in them we feele very often great battailes, whileſt the fleſhe
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:7610:44"/> luſteth agaynſte the Spirite. This peece, <hi>To whiche you bee called,</hi> declareth what maner of peace this is: namely an vnity which Chriſt by his guidaunce and authoritie hath conſecrated and eſtabliſhed among vs. For God hath ſo reconciled vs vnto himſelfe in Chriſt, that we ſhould liue among our ſelues and be of one mind and one accord. And he addeth In one body. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he ſignifieth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we can no otherwiſe accord with God, vnleſſe we agree together amonhſt our ſelues, as me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers of one bodye. Wheras he biddeth vs be thankfull, I do not ſo much refer it to the minding of good turnes, as to the mildneſſe of maners, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to take away doubtfulneſſe [in the morning] I had rather haue it thus, Be you louing, or, Shew your ſelues louing: and yet I confeſſe, if thankfulneſſe poſſeſſe our ſences, it cannot bee but we ſhall be very ready to nouriſh loue towarde one another among our ſelues.</p>
               <p n="16">
                  <hi>16 Let the word of Chriſt dwell in you.)</hi> Hee will haue the doctrine of the Goſpell to be well knowne vnto them. whereof wee maye gather with what ſpirite they are led at theſe dayes, who bitterly forbid the ſame to the people, and keepe a ſeditious and ruffling ſtir, (ſaying) that no peſtilence is more to bee ſhun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, than that the common people ſhould reade the Scripture. For in very deede Paule in this place ſpeaketh to men and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of all ſortes. neither will he haue them onely take a lighte taſte of the word of Chriſt, but he biddeth that it dwell in them: that is to ſay that it haue a ſure ſeate (in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) &amp; that largely, that they may haue a deſire to encreaſe dayly more &amp; more. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there is in many a prepoſterous deſire or affection in lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, whileſt they abuſe the word of God to ſerue their own am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, or elſe vayne curioſitie, or elſe do falſifie the ſame by ſome maner of meane: therefore he ioyneth withall, <hi>In all wiſdome.</hi> That we being taught thereby, may taſt and ſauour that which we ought. Furthermore he defineth briefely this wiſedome or taſte, (namely) That the Coloſſians teache themſelues. Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching in this place is taken for profitable erudition or inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, which auayleth to edifiing, as Rom. <hi>12.7.</hi> Hee whiche tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth (let him doe it) in teaching. Alſo <hi>2.</hi> Tim. <hi>3.16,</hi> All Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is profitable to teache. This is the true vſe of the worde of Chriſt. Nowe becauſe ſometime doctrine or teaching
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:7610:44"/> of it ſelfe is colde: and (as he ſayth) while it is but only ſhewed what is right, Vertue is prayſed and is full ill a colde: he doth withall put too an admonition, which is as it were a confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his doctrine, and a prick to prick them forwarde. Ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther meaneth he that the word of Chriſt ought to profite only e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery ſingular perſon of them, ſo that they ſhoulde teache them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, but he requireth at their handes that they ſhould teache and warne one another.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In pſalmes and himnes.</hi> He reſtraineth not the word of Chriſt to theſe ſpecialties, but hee doeth rather expreſſe that all our ſpeaches ought ſo greatly to be framed to edification, that euen thoſe that doe ſerue to mirth, may ſauor of nothing that is vain. as if he ſhould ſay, Leaue vnto vnbeleeuers this foliſhe delight, which they take of vayne and trifling ſportes and ieſtes. As for your ſpeeches not onelye which are graue, but alſo euen ſuche as be glad and merrye, let them contayne in them ſome profite. In ſteede of their bawdie, or at leaſt immodeſt and light and ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh ſonges: Hymnes and ſonges which may ſound out the praiſe of God become you. Furthermore vnder theſe three names, hee hath comprehended all kynde of Songes. which they common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly do thus diſtinguiſh, that a Pſalme may be that vnto whiche in ſinging ſome muſical inſtrument beſide the tongue is ioyned. A Hymne maye bee properlye a Songe of prayſe, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it bee ſong with a loude voyce or otherwiſe. A Song doeth not onelye contayne prayſes, but admonitions too, and other matters. But hee will haue the ſpirituall ſongs of Chriſtians, not ſuche as bee endited of friuolous trifles, and things of naught. For this hath relation to the argument. This peece <hi>In grace,</hi> Chriſoſtome diuerſlye expoundeth: but I take it ſimply, as alſo afterward in the <hi>4.</hi> chap. <hi>6.</hi> verſ. when hee ſayth, let your ſpeeche be poudered with ſalte, in grace. that is to ſay, poudered with ſuche a dexteritie or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ſomnes as maye bee gracious or acceptable, and by the commoditie and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite thereof maye pleaſe the hearers: that it maye bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarye to ſcoffing or knauerye or like Follies. <hi>Singing in your hartes.</hi> This belongeth to the affection, for as we oughte to ſtirre vp others, ſo alſo muſt we ſinge from our hart, that it bee not an outward ſounde of the mouthe onelye. Although
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:7610:45"/> it be not ſo to be taken, as though he bad euery one ſing inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to himſelfe: but he wil haue both ioyned together, ſo that the hartes go before the tongues.</p>
               <p n="17">
                  <hi>17 And whaſoeuer you doe.)</hi> Theſe wordes and that which goeth before, I haue already expounded in the Epiſtle to the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſians, where is the ſame almoſt worde for word. Becauſe hee had now begon to diſcourſe of the partes of a Chriſtian life, and had touched only a fewe preceptes: and that it was to long by peecemeale to runne thorowe the reſt: therefore in a groſſe ſumme hee concludeth, that our life is ſo to be ordred, that whatſoeuer wee ſaye or doe, it maye bee all ruled by the gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunce of Chriſt, and may haue reſpect to his glorye, as to the marke. For wee ſhall fitlye comprehende both theſe in this worde: namely that all our ſtudies and indeauoures haue their beginning at inuocating or calling vpon Chriſt, and ſue to his glorye. Out of inuocation followeth the bleſſing of God: which miniſtreth matter and occaſion of thanksgiuing vnto vs. And it is to be noted that he teacheth that thankes muſt be giuen to the Fathe by Chriſt, as by him we obtayne whatſoeuer good it is that God beſtoweth vpon vs.</p>
               <q>
                  <p n="18">18 Wiues be ſubiect to your own huſbands, as is comly in the Lord.</p>
                  <p n="19">19 Husbands loue your wiues: and be not bitter againſt them.</p>
                  <p n="20">20 Children obay your parents in all thinges. for this ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the Lord.</p>
                  <p n="21">21 Fathers prouoke not your Children, leaſt they bee diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayed.</p>
                  <p n="22">22 Seruauntes obay in all poyntes thoſe which according to the fleſhe are your Mayſters: not with giuing o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience before their eyes, as ſeeking to pleaſe men, but in ſimplicitie of the harte, as you whiche feare God.</p>
                  <p n="23">23 And whatſoeuer you ſhall doe, doe it from the hart, as vnto the Lord, and not vnto men:</p>
                  <p n="24">24 Knowing that of the Lord you ſhal receaue a reward of inheritance, for ye ſerue the Lord Chriſt.</p>
                  <p n="25">
                     <pb n="75" facs="tcp:7610:45"/>25 But hee that ſhall doe vniuſtly, ſhall beare the rewarde of his iniquitie: and there is no accepting of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</p>
               </q>
               <p n="18">
                  <hi>18 Wiues. &amp;c.)</hi> Now follow particuler dueties, as they cal them, whiche depende of euerye ones vocation: in handling of whiche it were ſuperfluous to beſtowe many wordes: becauſe I haue already in the Epiſtle to the Epheſians ſpoken almoſte as much as was needefull. Yet in this place I will breefly adde ſuch thinges as are properly agreeble to the opening of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent place. He commandeth women that they be ſubiect. This is playne: but that which followeth is doubtfull, [that is] <hi>as is comlye in the Lord.</hi> For ſome doe thus conſtrue it, <hi>Bee ye ſubiecte in the Lorde as is comelye.</hi> Yet I doe rather o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe conſtrue it, [that is] <hi>As is comelye in the Lorde,</hi> that is, according to the inſtitution of the Lorde: that hee maye confirme the ſubiection of women by the authoritie of the Lord. Of the huſbandes he requireth loue, and that they be not bitter: becauſe it is dangerous leaſt they abuſe their authoritie &amp; rule in becomming tyrants.</p>
               <p n="20">
                  <hi>20 Children obay your Fathers and mothers.)</hi> He enioi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth vnto Children that they obey their parents without excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. But what if their Parentes would driue them to doe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing that is vnlawfull: ſhal they than without choice or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde obay them alſo? But ſurelye it were more then heynous, ſetting God at naught, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the authoritie of men ſhould preuaile. I aunſwere, that here alſo muſt be vnderſtoode, that whiche is expreſſed, Ephe. <hi>6.1.</hi> namely in the Lorde. But to what pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe is the vniuerſall note, All things? I anſwere agayn, that he mighte ſhewe, that they muſt obaye not onelye their righte and iuſt commaundements, but alſo ſuch as are wrong and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſt. For many doe ſo forſooth ſhew themſelues obedient to their parentes, if it bee not a burthen or diſprofitable vnto them. But children oughte to remember this one thing, whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer Parentes they bee that they haue, that yet they happened vnto them by the prouidence of God, who hath by his ordinance made ſubiect the children vnto their Parentes. <hi>In all thinges</hi> than is, that they refuſe nothing, although the ſame be harde or
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:7610:46"/> greeuous: In all things, [is] that in things indifferent they yelde to their perſon: In all things, is that in ſeeking what be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth to themſelues, and in debating or beeing at variaunce, they take not vppon them that which is their right: but yet all this muſte be alwayes as farre as religon will pirmitte. Hee forbiddeth vnto parents ouer much ſharpeneſſe, leaſt ſo the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren be feared awaye from abiding any liberall or conuenient correction. For we ſee by dayly experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, of what force naturall and kinde education is.</p>
               <p n="22">
                  <hi>22 Seruaunts obay.</hi> Whatſoeuer is here reade concearning ſeruauntes, needeth no expoſition: becauſe it is already opened Ephe. <hi>6.1.</hi> except theſe two thinges, <hi>for you ſerue the Lorde Chriſt,</hi> And, <hi>he that ſhall doe vniuſtly, ſhall receiue the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde of vniuſt dealing,</hi> By the former ſentence hee meaneth thus, that they muſt ſo ſerue me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that Chriſt neuertheleſſe muſt holde the ſouerayntie in the Lorde, and that hee may be the hed Lorde. An excellent comfort truely to all that are in ſubiection, whileſt, for that they willingly ſerue their maiſters, they heare their obedience as acceptable to Chriſt, as though it were done vnto him, whereof alſo Paule gathereth that they ſhall receiue a rewarde of him: euen the rewarde of inheritaunce. whereby he ſignifieth that the ſelfe ſame thing that is repayde for works, is freely geuen vs of God. for the inheritaunce is by adoption. In the latter ſentence he doth agayne comforte ſeruauntes, for that, if they be oppreſſed with the vniuſt crueltie of their may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, God himſelfe wil reuenge it, nether yet will he paſſe euer ſuch iniuries as are done to them, becauſe they be ſeruauntes: ſeeing that with him there is no reſpecte of perſons. For this cogitation or thought might kill their hartes, if they thoughte that there were none or no greate reckoning made of them in the ſight of God, or elſe that their miſeries were not regarded. Moreouer it happeneth often that ſeruauntes themſelues will begin to take vpon them the reuenging of euill and vncourte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous handling. He therefore preuenteth this euil, when he admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſheth that they muſt tarry for the iudgement of God with for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearing.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:7610:46"/>
               <head>¶ The fourth Chapter.</head>
               <q>
                  <p n="1">1 Mayſters giue to your Seruauntes that which is right, and mutuall vprightneſſe,<note place="margin">Equalitie.</note> knowing that you alſo haue a mayſter in heauen.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Be inſtaunt in prayer, watching in the ſame, with thankes giuing.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Praye you in like manner for vs, that GOD maye open vnto vs the gate of ſpeeche to ſpeake the myſterie of Chriſt, for whoſe alſo cauſe I am a priſoner.</p>
                  <p n="4">4 That I maye make it apparaunte, euen as I oughte to ſpeake.</p>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>MAisters giue to your. &amp;c. <hi>Hee</hi>
                  </hi> putteth, <hi>that which is iuſt,</hi> in the firſt place, by which he meaneth that humanitie whereof hee gaue commaundement Ephe. <hi>6.8.</hi> But for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that the ſtate of Seruauntes is viewed of mayſters as it were from alofte, ſo that they thinke themſelues to be bounde by no Lawe: Paule bringeth them into courſe and order: becauſe both of them alike are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the imperie and commaundement of God. and hereof com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth this equalitie or rightneſſe whereof he maketh mention. <hi>And mutuall or like equabilitie,</hi> or indifferencie. Some doe otherwiſe expound it: but I doubt not but Paule in this place put <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> for right that is aunſwerable from one partie to an other, or that which one party giueth to another: as to the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſians he vſed <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. For mayſters haue not ſo their ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntes vnder them, but that they in like maner owe ſome duty vnto them: as conuenient and proportionable righte and equall dealing ought to bee in force among all ſortes of perſons.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2 Be inſtaunt in prayer.</hi> He returneth to generall exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:7610:47"/> in which we may not looke for an exact and ſtricte order: for if we did, hee ſhoulde beginne with prayer: but Paule hath not greatly reſpected that [<hi>viZ.</hi> order]. Furthermore in this place he ſetteth out two thinges in prayer, firſt continuance or often vſe thereof, after that readineſſe or an earneſt intente. For when he ſayth, Be inſtaunt, he exhorteth to perſeueraunce. Hee ſetteth <hi>Watching</hi> oppoſite vnto coldneſſe and careleſneſſe. Hee putteth to <hi>thankeſgiuing,</hi> becauſe that in ſuch wiſe God is to bee prayed too for our preſent neceſſitye, that in the mean while we forget not thoſe benefites which we haue alreadye receiued. Moreouer we ought not to be ſo importunate, that wee repine and bee diſpleaſed, if ſtraighte waye GOD fulfill not our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires and prayers, but with patient myndes to receyue whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer he ſhall giue. So there is two maner of thankesgiuing ne-neceſſarye. Of which poynt ſomething hath bene alſo ſayde Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lippians. <hi>4.6.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3 Praye you in like maner for vs.</hi> Hee doeth not counterfeite this: but becauſe he knewe his owne neceſſitie, he did in earneſt wiſhe to be helped with their prayers, and hee was perſwaded that the ſame would do him good. Who now dare then ſet light by the interceſſions of the bretheren, of which Paule confeſſeth himſelfe to haue neede? And certaynlye the Lorde hath not in vayne ordayned this excerciſe of charitie among vs, that one of vs ſhould pray for an other. Therefore euerye one oughte, not onely to praye for the bretheren, but interchaungeablye alſo to deſire ayde earneſtlye of other folkes prayers alſo, as oft as the matter ſo requireth. But childiſh is the argument or reaſon of the Papiſtes, who gather thereof that the dead are to bee called vpon, that they may pray for vs. For wherein is it like? Paule commendeth himſelfe to the prayers of the bretheren, with whom he knew that by the commaundement of God he had mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall communication, but who will not ſay that this reaſon (of mutuall communicating) ceaſeth in the dead? Therfore letting paſſe ſuch follies, let vs returne to Paule. as we haue in Paule a notable example of modeſtie, in that hee calleth vnto others to ayde and aſſiſt him, ſo alſo are we admoniſhed that it is a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter full of great difficultie, conſtantly to abide in the defence of the Goſpell, ſpecially when daunger doeth vrge. And not
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:7610:47"/> without cauſe doth he deſire the Churches in this cauſe to ayde him. And withall conſider his ardent zeale how meruailous it is. He is not carefull for his owne ſauegarde, hee deſireth not that prayers bee poured forth by the Churches for himſelfe, that hee may be deliuered from the daunger of death. Hee is content with this one thing, if he abide inuincible and vnfeare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in the profeſſion of the Goſpell. ſo ſecurely and vnfearefully doth he preferre the glorye of Chriſt, and the ſpreading abrode of the Goſpell before his owne life. But by the <hi>gate of ſpeeche,</hi> he playnely meaneth that which he calleth Ephe. <hi>6.19.</hi> the ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of his mouth: and that which Chriſte calleth Mouth and Wiſedome. For this maner of ſpeaking differeth nothing at al from that former in meaning, but onely in faſhion. For with an elegant Metaphor hath he in this place ſhewed playnelye, that it is neuer a whit more eaſie for vs, to ſpeak boldly touching the Goſpell, than to breake thorowe a gate that is ſhut and barred. For this is truelye the worke of God, as alſo Chriſte did ſaye, It is not you that ſpeake, but the Spirite of youre Father whiche ſpeaketh in you: <hi>Math 10.10.</hi> Hauinge therefore ſette forth the difficultie thereof, he pricketh forth the Colloſſians the more to praye, when he teſtifieth that hee cannot otherwiſe ſpeake rightly, except his tongue bee directed of the Lord. Secondly he draweth his argument from the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe of the things, when he calleth the Goſpell the <hi>myſterie of Chriſt.</hi> Neither muſt we ſlightly labour or take payns in ſo great a matter. Thirdly he maketh mention alſo of his danger.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <hi>4 As I ought.</hi> This peece augmenteth the difficultie: for hee meaneth that it is not a vulgar or common thing. To the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſians hee addeth, <hi>that I may boldly behaue my ſelfe.</hi> Whereof appeareth that hee wiſhed to himſelfe an vnfeare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full boldeneſſe and confidence, ſuch as becommeth the maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie of the Goſpell. Furdermore where as Paule doeth nothing here, but that hee wiſheth grace to bee giuen him to fulfill his office: let vs remember that it is a rule in like manner preſcribed vnto vs, that wee geue not place to the furye of the aduerſaries, but that wee labour and ſtriue euen to the death to ſette forthe the Goſpell. And becauſe that is aboue our abillitie and power, it is meete that wee bee inſtaunte
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:7610:48"/> in prayers, that the Lord leaue vs not deſtitute of the Spirite of boldneſſe.</p>
               <q>
                  <p n="5">5 Walke wiſely toward them that are without, redeeming the time.</p>
                  <p n="6">6 Let your ſpeeche alway be in grace poudered with ſalte: that you may know how you ought to anſwere to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery man.</p>
                  <p n="7">7 Tichicus a beloued brother and a faithfull miniſter and a fellow ſeruaunt in the Lord, ſhall make known vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you all mine affaires.</p>
                  <p n="8">8 Whom I haue ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vnto you for this cauſe, that you might know mine eſtate, and that your hartes mighte bee comforted.</p>
                  <p n="9">9 With Oneſimus a faithfull and beloued brother, which is of you. All thinges ſhall be made known vnto you which are here (done.)</p>
               </q>
               <p n="5">
                  <hi>5 Walke wiſely.</hi> He ſetteth them without, or forreyners, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite to them that are of the houſhold of fayth. For the Church is like a Citie, whoſe inhabitants are all faythfull, knit togea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with a mutual kindred or neighbourhood among the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues: and forreyners are the vnbeleeuers. But why will Paule haue theſe reſpected before the faythfull? There are three cauſes. Firſt that to the blinde there be no ſtumbling block layde. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe nothing is more ready than for vnbeleeuers by our vnwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rineſſe to be made worſe, and to haue their myndes wounded, ſo that they dayly more and more abhorre religion. Secondly that there be no cauſe and occaſion giuen them to ſlaunder the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, and ſo the name of Chriſt be layde forth to be mocked, they are made worſe, and turmoyles and perſecutions rayſed. Laſtly that while we keepe company with them at meate and other af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires, we be not ſtayned with their ſpotts, and by a little and a little waxe prophane and holye. To whiche purpoſe belongeth that which followeth, <hi>Redeemyng the tyme.</hi> Becauſe the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation of ſuch is daungerous, for Ephe. <hi>5.16.</hi> he ſheweth the reaſon, becauſe the dayes are euill: as if he ſhould ſaye, In ſo
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:7610:48"/> great corruption of the world the occaſion of well doing muſt be taken, and me muſt ſtriue with thoſe things that are lets. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore with how many the more ſtombling blocks our waye is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſed, ſo much the more attentiuelye muſt we beware that oure feete ſtumble not, or that we through ſlouth ſitte not ſtill idlely.</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <hi>6 Let your ſpeeche.</hi> He requireth pleaſantneſſe of ſpeeche, which may by the commoditie thereof allure the bearers. for hee doeth not condemne only ſuch ſpeeches as are apparantlye wicked or vngodly, but alſo ſuch as are of no accounte or idle. Therefore he biddeth that they be poudered with ſalte. Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane perſons haue their ſaltes or wittie ſayinges and conceits, but he ſpea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eth not of them: nay rather becauſe pleaſaunt and wittie conceates are plauſible, and for the moſt parte winne fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, he declareth after a ſort the faithfull from the vſe and cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of them, For he counteth it vnſauery, whatſoeuer it bee that edifieth not. In the ſame ſence is the worde <hi>grace,</hi> put: that it may be contrary to ſcoffing, and all kynde of fables and toyes which eyther hurt or elſe are vayn. <hi>That you may know how,</hi> He that hath accuſtomed himſelfe vnto circumſpecte ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, ſhall not fall into many abſurdities and inconueniences, into which thoſe that are ful of words, and bablers many times doe fall: but by continuall vſe hee will gette himſelfe know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge how to aunſwere well and directly. As agayne it muſte needes be that blabbe tongue fellowes doe ſette oute and offer themſelues to be mocked and laughed at as oft as they bee aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked a queſtion of any thing, wherein they ſuffer iuſt puniſhment for their fooliſh babling. Neyther doth he ſay only What, but alſo How (we muſt ſpeake): nor yet to all indifferentlye, but to euery (and ſinguler) perſon. For this is not the worſt poynte of prudencie and ſkill, to haue a conſideration of euery one.</p>
               <p n="9">
                  <hi>9 Myne affayres.</hi> To the end the Coloſſans may knowe what great care he hath ouer them, he doth confirme and aſſure them as it were with a pledge geuen. For whereas he was in priſon, and in hazarde of his life, without hauing regarde of himſelfe, he ſeeth to them, by ſending Tychicus vnto them. wherein ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth as well the ſingular zeale of the holye Apoſtle, as his
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:7610:49"/> prudencie and wit. for this is no ſmall matter, that whileſt he is helde priſoner, and is in extreame perill for the Goſpell, yet hee ceaſſeth not but giueth his diligence to promote and ſette for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde the Goſpell, and hath a care for all Churches. So his body iwis is ſhut in priſon, but his hart which is carefull, to doe as much as may be, ſpreadeth it ſelfe farre and wide. It is pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dencie and wit, in that he ſendeth a meete and diſcreete perſon that maye confirme and eſtabliſh them as muche as is needefull and that maye reſiſt and withſtande the wilineſſe of the falſe Apoſtles: moreouer for that hee keepeth ſtill with him Epa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phras, vntill they ſhall trie what and how greate a conſente in doctrine were among all the true teachers: and that they ſhall haue hearde the ſame of Tychicus that before they had learne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of Epaphras. Lette vs diligentlye conſider of theſe examples, that they maye ſtirre vs to the immitating of the like ſtudye and zeale. He putteth in Oneſimus alſo, to the ende the meſſage maye haue the more waight. Although it bee vncertaine who this Oneſimus was. for it is ſcant credible, that this is that Seruaunt of Philemon, becauſe the name of a Theefe and a runne awaye had bene in hazard reproche and miſliking. He ſetteth them both out with honeſt titles, that they maye doe the more good among them: and Tychicus ſpecially who was to vſeth office of teaching.</p>
               <q>
                  <p n="10">10 Ariſtarchus my priſon fellowe ſaluteth you, and ſo doeth Marke the Coſine of Barnabas: con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cearning whome you haue receyued commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dementes if hee come vnto you, that you receaue him.</p>
                  <p n="11">11 And Ieſus whiche is called Iuſtus, who are of the Circumciſion, theſe alone were workers with me into the kingdome of God, who were to me a comfort</p>
                  <p n="12">12 Epaphras ſaluteth you, which is of you a ſeruaunt of Chriſt, alwayes ſtriuing for you in prayers: that
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:7610:49"/> you may ſtande perfect and fulfilled in all the will of God.</p>
                  <p n="12">12 For I beare him witneſſe, that he hath great care o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer you, and ouer them who are at Laodicia and Hieropolis.</p>
               </q>
               <p n="10">
                  <hi>10 My priſon fellow.</hi> Hereby appeareth, that other came vnto Paule, after he was brought to Rome. And it is credible that his enemies at the firſt earneſtly laboured, to feare awaye by puniſhing them as they did him, all the godly from helping him, and that this preuayled for a time: but afterward ſome, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king harte vnto them, not to haue regarded whatſoeuer terrour was layde b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fore them. <hi>That you receaue him.</hi> Some bookes haue, Receaue him, in the imperatiue moode: but wrong for he expreſſeth that kinde of commaundement which the Coloſſians had receaued: namely that it was the commendacion of eyther Barnabas or Marke: which latter is more probable. In the greeke it is the infinitiue moode, but yet it muſt be ſo reſolued as I haue done it. And let vs marke that they were diligent in giuing teſtimonye: that they mighte diſcerne good men from falſe brethren, from dranes, from deceiuers, and many that were ſtraggelers and wanderers about. Which diligence and care is at theſe dayes more than neceſſarie: ether for becauſe vertuous teachers haue cold entertainment: or elſe for that foliſhe perſons and ſuch as are light of beleefe or ouer liberall bent and endaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gered to deceiuers.</p>
               <p n="11">
                  <hi>11 Theſe alone were workers.</hi> That is of them which were circumciſed: for he nameth others afterward, but thoſe vncir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed. He meaneth than that there were fewe Iewes at Rome which ſhewed themſelues helpers to the Goſpell: but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that the whole nation was aduerſarye to Chriſt. Although by Workers he vnderſtandeth them only which excelled in ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary giftes to further the Goſpel. But where was Peter at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tyme? Surely either he was ſhamefully paſſed ouer here, and not without iniury: or elſe they fable that holde he was then at Rome. Furthermore he calleth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpel <hi>the kingdom of God.</hi>
                  <pb n="84" facs="tcp:7610:50"/> for it is euen the ſcepter whereby God raigneth ouer vs, and by it we haue the adoption into life euerlaſting. But of this more is ſpoken in another place.</p>
               <p n="12">
                  <hi>12 Alwayes ſtriuing.)</hi> An example of a good Paſtor, who by meanes of diſtaunce of place doth in no wiſe forget the Church, but carieth the care thereof with him ouer the ſea. And note the force of the prayer, whiche is expreſſed in the worde, Stri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing. For although in this place Paule meante to note the vehemencie of affection, yet withall hee moniſheth the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſſians, that they account not the prayers of their Paſtor to be in vayne: but rather that they account them to bee no ſmall helpe to them. Laſtly let vs gather out of Paules wordes, that this is the perfection of Chriſtians, while they ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e fulfilled and in the will of God: leſt that they builde their purpoſe of life vpon any other thing elſe.</p>
               <q>
                  <p n="14">14 Luke the beloued Phiſitian ſaluteth you, and ſo doth Damas.</p>
                  <p n="14">14 Salute the Bretheren which are at Laodicea, and Nym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phas, and the Church which is at his houſe.</p>
                  <p n="16">16 And when the Epiſtle ſhall alſo bee reade among you, cauſe that it bee alſo read in the Church of the Lao<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicians: and that you reade that Epiſtle whiche is from Laodicia.</p>
                  <p n="17">17 And ſaye you to Archippus, Looke to the Miniſterie which thou haſt receaued in the Lord, that thou ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fill it.</p>
                  <p n="18">18 The ſalutation of Paule with myne owne hande. Bee myndefull of my bandes. Grace bee with you, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Sent from Rome, by Tichicus and Oneſimus.</head>
                  <p n="14">14 <hi>Luke ſaluteth you.)</hi> I am not of their mynds, who think
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:7610:50"/> this to be Luke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Euangeliſt, for I iudge he was better known than that there needed ſuch a kinde of ſhewing: and he ſhould haue bene ſet forth with a more worſhipfull title: certaynelye he would haue called him eyther his fellow helper, or at the leſt his faythfull and truſtye companyon, and partener of his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions &amp; buſineſſe. I rather coniecture that he was than away, and this other to be diſcerned from him by the name of a Phiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Although I contende not about it as being a certaintye: but I doe only bring coniectures. This Demas of whiche hee maketh mention, is the ſame without doubt whome he complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth afterwarde to haue forſaken him, 2. Tim. 4.10. When he ſpeaketh of the houſholde Church of Nymphas, let vs remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that in one houſhold is preſcribed of what faſhion it beſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth all the houſholders of Chriſtians to be: namely that they be ſo many ſmall Churches. Wherefore let euery man knowe, that this charge is layd vpon him, that he inſtruct his houſe in the feare of the Lord, that he keepe it vnder holy diſcipline, to be ſhort, that in the ſame he faſhion an Image or repreſentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Church.</p>
                  <p n="16">16 <hi>Let it be reade <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> Church of the Laodyceans.</hi> This Epiſtle howſoeuer it was entituled to the Coloſſians, yet ought it to profite other. The like muſte we thinke of all the Epiſtles. They were in deede written once to certain Churches by name: but becauſe they contayn a perpetuall doctrine, and that which is common to all ages: it makes no matter what title they haue. For the argu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap> and matter belongeth to vs. The other Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle whereof alſo he maketh mention, they haue thought, though vntruly, to haue bene written by Paule. They are twice decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued who haue thought Paul to haue writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the Laodicea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. I doubt not but that it was an Epiſtle ſent to Paule, the reading whereof might be profitable to the Coloſſians: as Cities are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed which are nere one to the other to haue many thinges common betwene them. And it was to groſſe a deceite, that, I wot not what Varlet, vnder this pretence, durſte ſubborne and counterfeite ſo vnſauerie an Epiſtle, that nothing could be deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed more contrary to the ſpirite of Paule [than it].</p>
                  <p n="17">
                     <pb n="86" facs="tcp:7610:51"/>17 <hi>Say ye to A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>chippus.</hi> As nere as I can geſſe, this Arch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus ſupplied the roome of the Paſtor, whileſt Epaphras was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way. It may happe he was not ſuche an one, as of himſelfe w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> ſtrong ynough, except he were pricked forth. Therefore Paules will is that he bee hartened on to doe the better at the motion of the whole Churche. He moughte haue warned him in his owne name: but he enioyneth the Coloſſians to doe it, to the ende they may knowe that they ought to prick their Paſtor forwarde alſo, if they ſee him to be colde, and the Paſtor him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe maye not refuſe to bee monyſhed of the Churche. For the Miniſters of the Worde are endewed with high power, but yet ſuche as is not looſe from Lawes. And therefore it is neceſſarie that they ſhewe the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>elues apte to learne, if they will teache others well. In that Paule doeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne ſette forth his bandes he declareth thereby that hee is not lightly or a little greeued. For hee was mindfull of humayne infirmitie: and without doubt he fete in himſelfe certayne pric<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings therof, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſo greatly deſired that all the godly ſhould be mindful of his trouble. But this is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſigne of diſtruſtfulnes, when he doth require on all ſides the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>des and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>lpes that by the Lord are appoynted him. The ſubſcribing of his hande, as elſewhere is ſeene, declareth that euen than there flewe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad forged Epiſtles, in ſo much that it was but neede to ſtoppe and preuent falſe dealing.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:7610:51"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
